<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rome is no rule, or, An answer to an epistle published by a Roman Catholic who stiles himself Cap. Robert Everard and may serve for an answer to two Popish treatises, the one entituled The question of questions, and the other Fiat lux, out of which books the arguments urged in the said epistle against the authority of the Scriptures and the infallibility of the Roman Church are collected : in which answer, the authority of the Scriptures is vindicated and the arguments for the Roman infallibility refuted / by J.I.</title>
            <author>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1103B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19570549</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19570549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1690:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rome is no rule, or, An answer to an epistle published by a Roman Catholic who stiles himself Cap. Robert Everard and may serve for an answer to two Popish treatises, the one entituled The question of questions, and the other Fiat lux, out of which books the arguments urged in the said epistle against the authority of the Scriptures and the infallibility of the Roman Church are collected : in which answer, the authority of the Scriptures is vindicated and the arguments for the Roman infallibility refuted / by J.I.</title>
                  <author>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 119 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for Livewel Chapman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Ives by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Everard, Robert, fl. 1664. --  Epistle to the several congregations of the nonconformists.</term>
               <term>J. V. C. --  (John Vincent Canes), d. 1672. --  Fiat lux.</term>
               <term>Mumford, J. --  (James), 1606-1666. --  Question of questions.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109129:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome is no Rule:</hi> OR, AN ANSWER To an Epiſtle
publiſhed by a Roman Catholick who ſtiles himſelf, Cap. ROBERT EVERARD
And may ſerve for an Anſwer to two Popiſh Treatiſes, the one
Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Queſtion of Queſtions;</hi> and the other, <hi>Fiat
Lux:</hi> out of which Books the Arguments urged in the ſaid Epiſtle
againſt the Authority of the Scriptures, and the pretended Infallibility of
the <hi>Roman</hi> Church are Collected. In which Anſwer, the authority of
the Scriptures is vindicated, and the Arguments for the <hi>Romiſh</hi>
Infallibility Refuted.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. I.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 8.17.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his
neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job. 6.25.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>How forcible are right words, but what do your arguings
reprove?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>Livewel
Chapman,</hi> at his Shop in <hi>Exchange Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornbil</hi>
1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109129:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109129:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the Word of God which he hath exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above all his Name,
to be as a light ſhining in a dark place, and as a Rule try Doctrines,
whether they are of Heaven, or of Men, is by <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> cried
down, as altogether inſufficient for that purpoſe; by <pb facs="tcp:109129:3"/>reaſon
whereof they have, and do daily beguile unstable Souls: I ſhall therefore, as
a preface to this enſuing Diſcourſe lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you the Judgement of
Christ and his Apoſtles, and diverſe of the Antient Fathers (who trode in
their paths) touching the Authority and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeſulneſs of the Holy
Scriptures, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with the Judgements of the <hi>Romane
Catholicks,</hi> that ſo trying all things, thou mayeſt hold firſt that
which is beſt. In the firſt place, it was the Judgement of Christ (whoſe
Judgement is believed by all Chriſtians to be Infallible) <hi>That Men ought
to ſearch the <pb facs="tcp:109129:3"/>Scriptures, Joh. 5.39.</hi> And that the reaſon
why the <hi>Jews</hi> did erre in the Doctrine of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was,
becauſe <hi>they did not know the ſcripture, Mark 12.24.</hi> He judged
that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the <hi>Jews</hi> did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, was, becauſe
<hi>they did not believe the Scriptures, Jo. 5.46.</hi> He judged the
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be <hi>Armour of proof againſt the Devil, Mat. 4.6, 7. He
confutes his Adverſaries by them,</hi> Joh. <hi>8.17.</hi> Mat. <hi>12.4,
5.</hi> This was alſo the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practiſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;
therefore they commend the <hi>Bareans</hi> for ſearching the Scriptures,
<hi>Acts 17.11.</hi> Hence <pb facs="tcp:109129:4"/>it was that they mightily convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the
Jews, ſhewing by the Scriptures, <hi>That Jeſus was the Chriſt, Acts
18.28.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle informs <hi>Timothy, That they were able to make
wiſe to ſalvation, and that they were profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof,
for Correction, and for Inſtruction in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, 2</hi> Tim.
<hi>3.15, 16. And that if we fulfil the Royal law according to the
ſcriptures, we ſhall do well,</hi> Jam. <hi>2.8. That they were written for
our</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, <hi>upon whom the ends of the</hi> world <hi>are come,
1</hi> Cor. <hi>10 11.</hi> And <hi>that they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning,
that we <pb facs="tcp:109129:4"/>through patience and comfort of the ſcriptures might have
Hope,</hi> Rom. <hi>15.4. This was alſo the judgment of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who
followed the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> St.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, upon the <hi>8.</hi> Pſalm, <hi>That God hath
bowed down the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the capacity of Babes and Sucklings, that when
proud men will not ſpeak to their capacity, himſelf might.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, the ſame Authour ſaith, <hi>That our Faith would
reel and totter if the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſcriptures did not ſtand
faſt,</hi> de Doct. Chriſt. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>37.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109129:5"/>
            <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are
eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and are expoſed to the capacity of every Servant
and Plow-Man, and Widow, and Boy, and therefore God Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſcriptures by
the hand of Publicans, Fiſher-men, Tent-makers, Neat-heards, and Unlearned
men, that none of the ſimple people might have any excuſe to keep them from
reading,</hi> Hom. 1. in Mat.</p>
            <p>Again be ſaith, <hi>That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is required to
ſalvation is all ſet down in ſcriptures, neither is there any thing
wanting there, that is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <pb facs="tcp:109129:5"/>for mans ſalvation,</hi> Hom.
<hi>41.</hi> in Mat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſaith, <hi>That we ſhould hear the
words of the ſcriptures, which are ſo plain and eaſie, that they need no
Expoſition, but to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, Dialogue</hi> cum Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.
<hi>213.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things men find
and feign without the Authority, and Teſtimony of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as if
they were from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Tradition are ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the ſword of
God,</hi> ſee Comment. in Hagg. Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other hand, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks ſay, <hi>The
ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <pb facs="tcp:109129:6"/>are no certain Rule, no Infallible guide; and that
all things neceſſary to ſalvation, are not contained in them;</hi> See
the Books Entituled, the <hi>Queſtion</hi> of <hi>Queſtions,</hi> and
<hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> and the Epiſtle Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Everard,</hi> to which
this Anſwer is Directed. They for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the People to uſe and ſearch them.
See <hi>Everards Epiſtle</hi> pa. <hi>14.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>Thoſe words
in the 5. of</hi> John <hi>are ſo far from being a Command to ſearch the
ſcriptures, that they rather ſeem a reprehenſion to all that have ſuch
a conceit of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again they ſay, <hi>The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <pb facs="tcp:109129:6"/>are fitted to
the time, and are variably underſtood; the ſenſe whereof being one while
this, and again, another while that, according as it pleaſeth the Church to
change her judgement.</hi> See <hi>Cuſan. Ep. 2.37.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, The Biſhop of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo's</hi> putting forth the Bible
in divers Languages, puts the Latine Tranſlation in the midſt between the
Hebrew and Greek, and then ſaith, <hi>the Greek and Hebrew he placed of
either ſide as two Thieves, and the Latine between them, as Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others of them call the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures <pb facs="tcp:109129:7"/>
               <hi>a noſe of
wax,</hi> that may be writhed any way, and a <hi>dumb Judge,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now whoever ſhall but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially lay the judgment, of theſe
men concerning the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and compare
them with what Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and their followers judged of them,
may eaſily ſee that there is more excellency in the gleanings of the
Scriptures, then in the full Vintage of the Pope and all his Cardinals; whoſe
Vines are like thoſe of <hi>Sodom,</hi> by reaſon whereof, the Nations have
been intoxicated, and made drunk with the wine of her fornication. <pb facs="tcp:109129:7"/>For if they were not drunk, they would never quit both Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and
Reaſon, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, all that by which they become both Men and
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to hearken to the voice of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Charmers, who
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they will want water to carry Proſelytes to the
<hi>Romiſh</hi> Sea, care not though they open the flood-gates of Atheiſm
and Antiſcripturiſm upon the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World. For who ſeeth not (but
he that is willing to be blind) that the arguments le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by them for wounding
the reputation of Scriptures, are as a ſharp ſword ready to paſs through
the reins of Chriſtianity <pb facs="tcp:109129:8"/>it ſelf. For the prevention whereof,
I have publiſhed this enſuing Anſwer, which I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be
impartially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Lord give you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all
things, and open your underſtanding, that you may underſtand the
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; that ſo taking to your ſelves the ſwords of the Spirit,
which is the word of God, you may be able to reſiſt all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries
of your pretious ſouls, who daily ſeek to make merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of you; and
that you may ſo do, ſhall be the Prayers, and Deſires of thy Friend,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109129:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Rome is no Rule:</hi> OR, An Anſwer to an Epiſtle
publiſhed by a Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick who ſtiles himſelf Cap. ROBERT
EVERARD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I ſhall engage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the main body of this
diſcourſe, I ſhall take a view of its Front and Rear, I mean the Title
and Poſt-ſcript: In the Title you have the ſuperſcription of <hi>An
Epiſtle to the ſeveral Congregations of Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109129:9"/>
            <p>Here I would gladly be informed who you mean by this term of
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination, <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> either you mean all that Conform
not to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or all that Conform not to the Church of
<hi>England;</hi> if you mean all that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not to the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> then the Church of <hi>England</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this
Epiſtle, and rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned by you among all other Sects and Hereticks: but if by
<hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi> you would diſcriminate all that Conform not to
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then your Mother the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Holy Catholick
Church is concerned in your Epiſtle, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi>
to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as well (or rather as ill) as others; and
good reaſon ſhe ſhould be concerned, ſince ſhe hath furniſhed you
with all your Weapons for this Warfare out of here Armoury: and it is but a
piece of gratitude to direct that to her <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109129:9"/>which you ſo
lately received from from her: for he that hath a hand to take, and not a
tongue to return thanks, deſerves for the future to be both lame and
dumb.</p>
            <p>Having viewed the Superſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I come to the Subſcriber,
and he is no leſs then a Captain, <hi>Captain Robert Everard.</hi> But where
was he a Captain, and whom did he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand? Let him ſpeak for himſelf he is
old enough. He tells us <hi>he was at the head of a Troop in the rebellious
Army:</hi> See his <hi>Poſt-ſcript, p.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>But what a ſhame is this, that this Honour was not laid in the
duſt, rather then prefixed in the Title of a Book? Surely had you been truly
humbled for that Rebellion, as you pretend, you would have ſaid of all the
honour that you acquired thereby, as <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſaid of his Idols;
<hi>What have I to do any more with you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109129:10"/>the
place where this Epiſtle was printed, and if you will believe it, it was
printed at <hi>Paris.</hi> I ſee you have learned one, if not all the the
three things which a learned man obſerves Children ſoon learn of their
Mothers, Pride, Revenge, and Lying: this laſt appears in that you have made a
Lye your refuge, by ſaying your Epiſtle was printed at <hi>Paris.</hi> But
let me ask you the Queſtion which you ask your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>p.</hi> 20.
<hi>who will adventure</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to make oath the Scriptures we
have, agree with the Originals?</hi> So ſay I, Who will adventure to make
oath that this Epiſtle was printed at <hi>Paris?</hi> Surely we are like to
meet with little truth in the Houſe when a Lye in Capitals, and a Capital Lye
is inſcribed on the Porch, as a <hi>London</hi> Printer will witneſ, to
your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, if occaſion
ſerve.</p>
            <p>I come now to the Poſt-ſcript,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herein you caution your
Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109129:10"/>
               <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>to ſet down your own
words as they lye intirely, without maintaining them:</hi> and alſo, <hi>if
he anſwers by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraphs, to ſet down your whole Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, give me leave to tell you, that you require a thing
impoſſible; for there is in your Epiſtle ſo little of you, as any one
may perceive (by your own words) and by comparing it with the Book Entituled,
(<hi>The Queſtion of Queſtions,</hi> and <hi>Fiat Lux</hi>) that it is hard
to ſay whether any thing by yours beſides theſe three words, CAPTAIN
ROBERT EVERARD, and therefore if you would have had a diſtinct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to
all your Arguments, you ſhould have diſtinguiſhed what had been yours,
from what was other mens, by a different Character, as is uſual in ſuch
caſes.</p>
            <p>You go on in your Poſt-ſcript and forewarn your Reſpondent,
<hi>that be ſet not up a Puppit of his own in <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109129:11"/>ſtead of
Anſwering.</hi> If he doth ſet up a Puppit of his own, he hath done more
then you, who have ſcarce ſet up any thing of your own, beſides your
name. <hi>But</hi> (what) <hi>if be ſet up a Puppit of his own and call it
yours,</hi> (you ſay) <hi>he will not make your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, but his own
ridiculous.</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he may poſſibly make his own, but he cannot make
your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ridiculous, becauſe he knows not any one that is yours in all
the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>The next thing you caution your Reſpondent is, <hi>That he would
forbear all reproaches and ſlanders againſt the Catholick Church, or
Catholicks in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or in particular, which</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is a fault
Protestants are too much in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral addicted to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I perceive this Counſel is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier given then taken,
elſe why do you reflect reproach upon Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in general in the ſame
breath, in which you invite them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear reproaches?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:109129:11"/>
            <p>Again, You ſay, <hi>That the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Independents do
by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks as they did by his late Majesty of glorious memory, and with
our moſt dread Soveraign that now is, and their Party,</hi> (viz.) <hi>to
impute crimes to them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, and errours innumerable, without taking
care to examine whether what they charged was true or falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I have four or five things to ask you; 1 Whether you did
uſe to do ſo by the Kings Majeſty when you were an Independent, and at
the head of your Rebellious Troop? 2 Whether you believe the Kings Majeſty
hath pardoned you and all that were ſo wickedly minded? 3 Whether ſince you
were pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you would have any to upbraid you with thoſe pardoned Crimes?
If not, then 4 Why do you that pretend to ſo much Charity, do that to others,
you would not be done unto? Laſtly, Why do you violate the Law of your
Soveraign, who <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109129:12"/>hath forbidden upon a penalty, that thoſe
things ſhould be remembred againſt any that he hath been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bury
in Oblivion? But Sir, if you were not a Novice in the Catholick Way, you might
know that the people you are now fallen in with, have been the moſt guilty
(in ſpeaking evil of, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil to men in Authority) of any that ever
mentioned the Name of Chriſt; witneſs their traducing King <hi>Henry</hi>
8. for that ever to be admired, and to be remembred work of his, in throwing
off the Popes Supremacy; how have the Romaniſts reported it as a
Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of his Luſt and Levity? How then can they have any regard to
the preſent Rulers, who daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile their Predeceſſors, wherein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of
them have acted againſt their Intereſts? witneſs both the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder
Treaſon, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. And what good Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109129:12"/>can his Majeſty that now is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from you? Who
forſaking a People that deſtroyed one King, and pretending repentance for
that, go and joyne with a people whoſe Principle is to Depoſe and Deſtroy
Kings.</p>
            <p>Paſſing from your Title and Poſt-Script, I now come to
Encounter with the main Body of your Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: In the Front whereof
<hi>You</hi> place a Text out of the great St. <hi>Austine</hi> againſt
<hi>Manicheus,</hi> whoſe Words are theſe; <hi>If thou ſhalt find any one
who doth not as yet believe the Goſpel, what wilt thou do when he ſhall
ſay unto thee, I do not believe? But neither had I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the Goſpel,
unleſs I had been thereunto moved by the Authority of the Catholick Church:
Thoſe therefore to whom I ſubmitted, when they required me to believe the
Goſpel; why ſhould I not yield Obedience to them, when they perſwade me
not to believe</hi> Maniche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:109129:13"/>
            <p>Thus ſpeaks <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and more to the ſame
purpoſe: lo which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That this Text out of <hi>Auſtine</hi> may
be applyed to any Church as well as to yours; And if the Church of
<hi>England</hi> ſhall perſwade any one that is a <hi>Jew,</hi> to turn,
and become a Chriſtian, may he not ſay he did well to believe them when
they perſwaded him to believe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel? Why therefore ſhould he not
believe them when they perſwade him not to turn Roman Catholick? But to this
Text I ſhall ſubjoyne Two Texts more out of the ſame Authour againſt
the <hi>Donatiſts: The Queſtion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>between Us and
the</hi> Donatiſts, <hi>is, where is the Church?</hi> This is the Queſtion,
between the Proteſtants and the Romaniſts; He Anſwers, <hi>Let not
theſe Speeches be heard among you; This I ſay and this thou ſayest, but
let us hear what the Lord ſayes: There are certain Books of God, unto whoſe
Authority we both conſent. <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109129:13"/>There let us try our Cauſe;
There let us ſeek the Church: And again in the Scriptures, have we learned
Chriſt; In the Scriptures, have we learned the Church,</hi> Ep. 166. <hi>ad
Donatift.</hi> Whoſoever ſhall compare theſe Texts out of
<hi>Auſtine,</hi> may eaſily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf. What his Judgment was
in the Queſtion between You and Us, <hi>(viz.)</hi> whether we ſhould learn
Chriſt and the Scriptures from the Church, or whether we ſhould learn
Chriſt and the Church from the Scriptures? To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſpeaking of a Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, Saith; <hi>This Man is found
differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the</hi> HOLY SCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TURES, <hi>as will appear to all Men that
Read attentively: If he then diſſent from them, he is altogether an Alien
to the Holy Catholick Church, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.
<hi>haer.</hi> 48. It ſeems in his time, all men were permitted to read the
Scriptures attentively, to inform iheir minds in the Truth; <pb n="12" facs="tcp:109129:14"/>whatever is now a dayes pretended to the contrary.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to the Epiſtle it ſelf; In the beginning
whereof, <hi>Page</hi> 1. You give an account of the Reaſons of its
Publication; which are; <hi>To Anſwer Expectation, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the World from
cenſuring, and to manifest your charity to your late dear Brethren, from whom
you have received returns of Aſſection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did expect that among thoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that prevailed with you
to publiſh the grounds of your change; I ſhould have found you ſaying,
that the Glory of God had been the chief moving Cauſe: But I finde not a word
of that, and therefore however you may have Anſwered the Expectations of
others; I am ſure you have not anſwered mine.</p>
            <p>But further you ſay, you publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Epiſtle, <hi>To
prevent the World from cenſuring:</hi> Sir, whatever you promiſed your
ſelfe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109129:14"/>of your Book, your heart fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for fear of obtaining, when you had finiſhed it; And therefore you are forced
to Ride Poſt after your Reader, and pray him, <hi>That he would not up-braid
you; As if you had ſome private ends of your own, in your preſent
change:</hi> See the Poſt-Script in <hi>Page</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>Which plainly ſhews that you had ſome miſ-givings of heart,
that all you had ſpoken throughout your Book would not Anſwer your end,
<hi>(Viz.) Keep the World from cenſuring.</hi> And as for that other end,
which you pretend in the publiſhing of your Book; Namely, <hi>Charity to your
late Brethren.</hi> Truly whatever you pretend, they will ſcarce believe you,
becauſe in your Poſt-Script you uncharitably impute the Calumnies and
Slanders that were caſt upon his late Majeſty, and his Majeſty that now
is, to the Preſbiterians, and Independens Indefinitly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109129:15"/>exception: Is this Charity? And this uncharitableneſs of
yours, is grievouſly aggravated; Firſt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is baſely remembred
by you, who were in the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation with others; And, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
Becauſe it is mentioned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it hath been pardoned by the Kings Majeſty;
And is this your gratefull return for that love which your late Brethren have
manifeſted to you? If ſo, ſurely the charity of a Catholick, and the
mercies of the wicked, are alike cruel.</p>
            <p>You proceed like a Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and in the latter end of
<hi>page</hi> the 1. Sound a Trumpet in your own praiſe, by ſaying,
<hi>That your carriage was alwaies ſuch,</hi> (while you was in Communion
with them (meaning your late Brethren) <hi>As gave them ſufficient reaſon
to believe that you was not Byaſſed by world intereſts and ſelfiſh
conſiderations.</hi> But if any body believes ſo, they may erre; 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109129:15"/>becauſe they do not believe as the Church believes.</p>
            <p>In the Second Page, you tell us, how you came to be acquainted
with a Lay Gentle-Man of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick perſwaſion, and how he
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogated you about the grounds of Chriſtian Religion: The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
of his Queſtions was to this purpoſe; <hi>Whether you were ſure the
Christian Religion in General was more true then the Religion of</hi> Turks,
Jews, <hi>or any others,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>The Reaſon he gave for this
queſtion was, that if neither your ſelf, nor thoſe that taught you, that
Chriſtianity was the only ſafe way to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was infallibly certain; or
were capable of any mistakes or errour in this thing: Then it followed that
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity was but probable, and not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From Page ſecond, to the eighth, you recite what Arguments your
Catholick Friend uſed to prove theſe things to you, <hi>(Viz.) That we 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109129:16"/>could not convince a</hi> Turk <hi>or a</hi> Jew <hi>of the
certainty of Christianity but by the Churches Infallibility;</hi> Which I
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to make a reply unto, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is but a Narrative of a
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conference between you and that Catholick Gentle-Man; And chiefly
becauſe I ſhall have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeake to the very ſame things in
my following Anſwers to your Arguments, to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>You come in the latter end of the 8. <hi>Page,</hi> to tell us
what Effects this Conference had upon your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; as that thereupon,
<hi>You reſolved to have Recourſe to Almighty God by Prayer for his Divine
aſsiſtance, and to make it your buſineſſe according to your skill and
underſtanding, to take a full view of the Catholick Faith, and of
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and laying aſide all Prejudices, Pride, and Humours; You
Reſolved to embrace (by the aſsſtance of God) what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you ſhould
underſtand to agree to <pb n="17" facs="tcp:109129:16"/>his moſt Holy Will and
Pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon let me aske you a few queſtions; Firſt, how are you
ſure you had a Divine Aſſiſtance in this choice, as an Anſwer to your
Prayers, ſince when you made theſe Prayers, you were not a member of your
pretended Catholick Church? Secondly, How are you ſure, ſince the heart of
Man is deceitfull, that your heart did not deceive you, when it inclined you to
Popery? Thirdly, When you ſay you made this ſearch according to the
utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of your underſtanding, how do you infallibly know that your
underſtanding was not depraved, and that you were not given over to an
injudicious mind? Fourthly, Did you not pretend to have uſed the ſame means
to find out the true Church when you turned an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, as you did when
you did turn Papiſt? Laſtly, If ſo, how are you more able to Anſwer the
<hi>Turk</hi> 
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109129:17"/>or <hi>Jew</hi> now, then you were when your
Catholick Friend began to diſcourſe with you?</p>
            <p>In the latter end of <hi>p.</hi> 8. and the beginning of the 9.
You ſay, that <hi>You gathered from</hi> Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.6. Mark 16.16. Eph. 4.5. 2 Cor. 10.45. Heb 10.13.
<hi>From all which scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (where God requires Faith)</hi> you ſay)
<hi>you thought it did naturally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that there muſt be ſome means
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, by which we may know this true faith from all falſe
Opinions, or elſe you ſay,</hi> p. 10. <hi>that propheſie would be
ineffectual,</hi> Eſay 35. <hi>Say to them that are of a fearfull heart, Be
ſtrang, fear not, hebold your God will come and ſave you: Then the eyes of
the blind ſhall be opened, and the eares of the deaf ſhall be
unſtopped,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There ſhall be one high way, and a way, and it
ſhall be called the holy way; the way faring men, though fools ſhall not
erre therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:109129:17"/>
            <p>Now ſince God hath appointed ſuch a way; <hi>Your great
difficulty</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is to finde out the Rule and the Judge, ſince
one party propoſeth the ſpirit to be his guide; a Second, propoſeth
Reaſon to be his Rule; A Third, propoſeth Scriptures; The Fourth
aſſigneth the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You anſwer to the Firſt, and ſay, <hi>That the ſpirit
bearing witneſs with our ſpirts, or in plain terms, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſpirit
is not that judge:</hi> Your reaſon is, <hi>becauſe any one, whether he be
Jew, Pagan, or Chriſtian, if he have but confidence enough may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to
the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince (you ſay) the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty is to finde out the
Rule, I would gladly know how this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty ſhall be infallibly
reſolved? For if the private ſpirit within me muſt not reſolve me, nor
my reaſon muſt not be my Rule, nor the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures my Guide; then I have no
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109129:18"/>light left me to ſhew me the Church, but the Church. Thus
they deal like thieves, put out all other lights, that ſhould diſcover them
but their own dark lanthorn; But if you ſhall ſay that you prove the Church
by Miracles; How ſhall I be ſatisfied that thoſe Miracles are not
deluſions? Since as many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the ſpirit that have it not; So many
pretend to miracles that have them not: Then we muſt have faith to believe
thoſe miracles are true, and if they are true, they are no otherwiſe true
but by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: Then it is the ſame ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity to believe
miracles by the ſpirits teſtimony, as it is to believe the Scriptures by
the ſpirits teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: But this alſo implies a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, for if I
muſt finde the Church by the light of the ſpirit, perſwading me that
ſhe doth thoſe miracles by the power of God, then
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave you contradicted your ſelf,
by <pb n="21" facs="tcp:109129:18"/>ſaying, <hi>The ſpirit is not the guide:</hi> But
further, may not a man as well ſay that he believes he hath the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by
the ſpirit; and that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the Scriptures by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; as you
ſay, you believe the Church by the Church. I am ſure the laſt is the
greateſt abſurdity, and may not a Turk ſay the ſame for his way, that
he believers Mahomet by Mahomet, and the Alcoran by the Alcoran, (as you
believe) the Church by the Church. Now if you ſhall ſay, you believe the
Church by the Scripture, then the queſtion will be, how you know them to be
the Word of God? If you ſay, becauſe the Church teaches they are ſo; then
you run round (like a horſe in a Mill) proving the Church by the Scripture,
and the Scripture by the Church.</p>
            <p>You give another Reaſon, why the ſpirit witneſſing within
us, is not the guide appointed by God, <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109129:19"/>
               <hi>(becauſe by
this none that ever pretended to it did reconcile differences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray let charity begin at home; if your Church be ſo infallible;
why do not you decide the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that are between the Jeſuites, and the
Dominicans? hath not as endleſs controverſies ariſen among you? Hath not
as many Errours, and Schiſmes ſprung from you, as from any People
profeſſing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity? And would not your diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be greater, if
the power of the Sword did not prevail more then your pretended Infallibility?
And whereas you ſay, <hi>St.</hi> John <hi>preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth a Rule to know the
Spirit of Truth, from the Spirit of Errour,</hi> 1 Joh. 4. <hi>We are of God,
he that knoweth God hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, and he that is not of God, heareth not us;
Hereby we know the Spirit of Truth, from the Spirit of Errour.</hi> Now what is
this to your purpoſe, unleſs you would ſtill beg the queſtion; That
your Church and her Doctors, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:109129:19"/>are intended in thoſe words,
WE and US? But what if it be proved that you do not hear the Apoſtles? Then
it follows by the Text, and your own Argument, that you have the Spirit of
Errour. Now the Apoſtle taught that a Man ſhould examine himſelf, and
ſo let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup; but you deny the cup to
the common people; is this hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtles? The Apoſtle al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the
Biſhops to be Huſbands of one Wife; but you forbid that they ſhould have
any at all. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles would not have Prayers ſaid in a Language that
the People under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not; but you command it. Chriſt and the Apoſtles
command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a diligent reading, and ſearching of the Scriptures; but you
forbid it, and yet you are the only Men that muſt be heard, though you teach
contrary to Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:109129:20"/>
            <p>You go on, and ſay, <hi>That Reaſon muſt not be our Judge,
becauſe it muſt ſubmit to the Judge as a Subject, &amp;c.</hi> I pray,
what was your Judge? who reſolved the queſtion which you ſay, <hi>had
ſo much difficulty in it (viz.)</hi> who ſhould direct you whether any
Church was Infallible, or no? or where that Church was to be found? Did your
reaſon guide you in this ſearch or no? If it did not, I do not wonder you
made no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter choiſe, but you ſay, <hi>Reaſon is not your Rule,
becauſe it was to ſubmit as a Vaſſall to that Rule and Judge.</hi> But
Sir, Though the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (which you call your Judge) do
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſuch a Lordſhip over the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Men, I am ſure you
have given no reaſon why it ſhould be ſo. You ſay Reaſon is apt to
mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake; and therefore we ought not to be governed by it: But Sir, what if I
ſay the Pope is apt to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake; and therefore I ought not to 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109129:20"/>be governed by him. I am ſure, if that be made to appear
in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Reaſon, then Reaſon will guide me to decline following
ſuch a blind Guide. As for example, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> that was Pope about
the year 350 fell into <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the unjuſt
excommunicating <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, The Council of <hi>Constance</hi> depoſed Pope
<hi>John</hi> 23. where it was proved that he held <hi>there was no eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
life, nor Immortality of the ſoul, nor Reſurrection of the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray Sir, let Reaſon judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I may follow ſuch a
Catholick Guide.</p>
            <p>You add a third Reaſon to prove <hi>that Reaſon is not judge
in matters of Faith, for then</hi> (ſay you) <hi>it would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that it is
poſſible to pleaſe God, for Reaſon would teach us how to pleaſe
him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May not a man from the ſame Premiſes infer that your Church is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109129:21"/>not the Judge? becauſe then it would follow that it is
poſsible to pleaſe God without Faith, becauſe the Church would teach us
how to pleaſe him. But you will ſay the Church doth teach us to pleaſe
God by Faith; I ſay it is well if ſhe do: But what is this to the
purpoſe, ſhe did not teach us to pleaſe God by Faith before it was
required, and made known to us that God would be ſo pleaſed. In like
manner, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will direct a man to do the ſame when he is informed God
requireth ſuch a duty. But muſt not the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, nor my private Spirit,
nor my Reaſon judge? I pray then tell me how I ſhall be the better for all
you have written? for if my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt not judge of the fallibility, and
infallibility of your Arguments, then you had as good have told your late
Brethren thus: <hi>My B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tren, I
ſee that there is a great difference and contention among us, whether the
Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <pb n="27" facs="tcp:109129:21"/>Church be infallible or not; This Controverſie
cannot be judged by a private Spirit, for that may ſail; nor by Reaſon,
becauſe mens Reaſons are uncertain, and ſubject to variation; neither are
the Scriptures an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judge of Controverſies, therefore they cannot
judge of this: Let me therefore adviſe you of a way to decide this
queſtion. Firſt, Agree that the Roman Church is infallible, and then your
contention, whether the Roman Church be infallible, will ſoon be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. An
excellent advice, becauſe</hi> (you ſay) <hi>all other ways to judge and
decide controverſies are fallable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You now come in the third place to enquire whether the Scripture
be ſufficient to teach us the true Faith, &amp;c. (You ſay) <hi>You found
this high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended for, and ſeveral rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons urged for it.</hi>
Firſt, <hi>The words of our Saviour,</hi> John 5.39. Search the Scriptures,
for in them you think to have eternal life, and they <pb n="28" facs="tcp:109129:22"/>are
they which teſtifie of me. <hi>To this Text</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you found
ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral anſwers given which were ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; I That it doth not
appear whether this in the Original be the Im perative or the Indicative Mood,
St.</hi> Cyril (you ſay) <hi>with whom</hi> Beza <hi>agrees) takes it in the
Indicative Mood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a ſtrange Mood are you in then, to give an Anſwer to a
Text which (you ſay) you were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied withal? And in the ſame breath
(you ſay) it doth not appear whether it be the Imperative or the Indicative
Mood. Do you think infallibility had any aſſinity with this Anſwer? Nay,
you further ſay, <hi>that they are ſo farr from being a Command to all to
road and ſearch the Scriptures, that they</hi> RATHER SEEM <hi>a
Reprehenſion to all that ſhall frame that Conceit of them.</hi> But how can
this ſenſe of that Text be Catholick, when in ſtead of an 
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109129:22"/>infallible Expoſition, you tell us it RATHER SEEMS to be
ſo then otherwiſe? But what if I ſhould tell you that thoſe words
(Search the Scriptures) <hi>rather ſeem</hi> a Command then a Reprehenſion?
I ſhould <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeem</hi> to be infallible then you. You ſay, <hi>If
it be the Indicative Mood, the ſenſe will run thus.</hi> You do ſearch
the Scriptures, and <hi>ſo it ſeems to be a Reprehenſion.</hi> But this
is a ſenſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Chryfoſtome, Hom.</hi> 39. <hi>in Joan.
Chriſt</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſends us to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the
Scriptures;</hi> then it cannot be that he ſhould reprehend them. And the
Colledge of <hi>Rhems</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Text as we do, give this
Interpretation of it, <hi>He</hi> (viz.) <hi>Chriſt reprehendeth the
Jews</hi> (not for read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but) <hi>that reading dayly the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and
acknowledging that in them they ſhould find life; that yet they viewed them
ſo ſuperficially, that they could not find therein him to be Chriſt,
their King, Lord, Life, and <pb n="30" facs="tcp:109129:23"/>Saviour.</hi> And in the
Marginal Note upon this Text, they ſay, <hi>that neither Jews nor Hereticks
find the truth, becauſe they ſearch not the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures deeply, but read
ſuperficially.</hi> See <hi>Rhemiſh Annot.</hi> upon <hi>John</hi> 5. Now
ſee how you contradict your ſelves, you ſay the Scriptures are ſo far
from being a Command to all to read and ſearch, that they rather ſeem to be
a reprehenſion to all that ſhall frame that conceit of them. And your
<hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators ſay that they are reprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed becauſe
they did not ſearch deep enough, for if they had, they might have found
Jeſus to have been their <hi>Chriſt, their King, Lord, Life, and
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> And how can the ſaid Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators give that as a reaſon, why
<hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ews and Hereticks did not
find the Truth, becauſe they did not ſearch the Scriptures deep
enough.</hi> If either of theſe two opinions of your be true, 1 That men are
reprehended for <pb n="31" facs="tcp:109129:23"/>ſearching the Scriptures. 2 That the
Scriptures are not an infallible guide to direct us to find the Truth, if the
whole Colledge have tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated and interpreted truly, then ſurely you and
many of your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſpeak falſly. But if you ſhall ſay the Scriptures
may direct Jews and Hereticks to the truth, becauſe they direct them to the
Church, which is the Pillar of Truth: then it follows, 1 That both Jews and
Hereticks ought to ſearch the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures deeply, to find out the true
Church. 2 It muſt reſt upon their private judgments of diſcretion to
determine within themſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> or the
<hi>Proteſtants</hi> be that true Church, after they have made this deep and
diligent ſearch. 3 It follows that the Scripture is an infallible guide,
being deeply and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſearched; and that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why both Jews
and Hereticks err, is not the fallibleneſs of the <pb n="32" facs="tcp:109129:24"/>Scriptures, but want of diligent and deep ſearch; which being
uſed, they might have found Chriſt to have been their King, Lord, Life, and
Saviour; they might have found the Truth, and the Church, and conſequently
all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Eternal life.</p>
            <p>You come in the 14 <hi>pag.</hi> to give a ſecond reaſon why
the words (ſearch the Scriptures) <hi>cannot extend to prove the
concluſion; becauſe</hi> (you ſay) <hi>if they were uuderſtood in the
Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative Mood (which cannot infallibly be proved becauſe) they cannot be
profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to work Faith in them that cannot read, which</hi> (you ſay)
<hi>are the greateſt part of Mankind.</hi> (You ſay) it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not infallibly
be proved that thoſe words, <hi>ſearch the Scripture,</hi> are in the
Imperative Mood: but have you that pretend to Infallibility, proved that they
are in the Indicative Mood. What a madneſs is this, that you ſhould exact
infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109129:24"/>from thoſe that do profeſs
fallibility, and not perform an infallible Interpretation, when you pretend to
be guided by a Church that is infallible! But you ſay that <hi>if they were
underſtood in the Imperative Mood, they cannot work Faith in thoſe that
cannot read.</hi> But then it ſeems they may work Faith in them that can
read, becauſe (as the <hi>Rhemists</hi> ſay) they can ſhew both Jews and
Hereticks the Truth, if they ſearch deeply and diligently. But ſecondly,
How can general Councilsſhew the Truth and beget Faith, ſince (if they are
infallible) every body cannot read their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Canons? If you ſay they
underſtand thoſe Decrees and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, by the general Conſent of thoſe
that can read, then by the ſame means may a man that cannot read the
Scripture be guided by them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 You ſay, that by <hi>thoſe words <pb n="34" facs="tcp:109129:25"/>(ſearch the Scripture) cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that the Scriptures
ſhould be our Judge and guide, becauſe then they would have excluded
Chriſt, and after him his Apostles from being the infallible means by which
true Faith was to be taught to the World.</hi> But how doth this follow,
ſince you ſay the Church under the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was a Judge, and an
infallible guide. But did their being an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible guide till Chriſt,
exclude Chriſt from being a guide: and did Chriſts being a guide when he
was on the Earth, exclude the Holy Ghoſt from being a guide when he left the
Earth? In like manner it followeth not, becauſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of the Old
Teſtament (for of them Chriſt ſpeaks in the place under debate) were a
guide to inſtruct men into the knowledge of the Meſsiah, that they ſhould
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Him, His Spirit, or Apoſtles from being Guides. But further it 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109129:25"/>followeth by the ſame parity of Reaſon, that if the
Scriptures of the Old Teſtament could not be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible guide, becauſe
then they would have excluded Chriſt, and after him his Apoſtles from being
infallible guides. I ſay it follows by the ſame reaſon, that if Chriſt
and his Apoſtles were infallible Guides and Judges in matters of Faith, that
then they have excluded the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from being that infallible
Guide and Judge which ſhe pretends her ſelf to be: and thus you have
ſharpned a Knife to cut your Mothers throat.</p>
            <p>You pretend <hi>pag.</hi> 14. and ſay, <hi>that the ſecond
Reaſon that is urged for ſole Scripture being a guide, is</hi> 2
<hi>Tim</hi> 3.15. From a child thou haſt known the Holy Scriptures, which
are able to make thee wiſe to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through faith, which is in
Chriſt Jeſus. All Scripture is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Inſpiration of God, and is 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109129:26"/>profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for
inſtruction in righteouſneſs: that the man of God may be perfect,
throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to all good works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Text</hi> (you ſay) <hi>proves not what is
intended</hi> (viz.) <hi>that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture alone was the way, the rule, and
means appointed by God to judge and decide all doubts, &amp;c. your
Reaſons</hi> pag. 15. <hi>are, Firſt, That though They might be profitable
to ſuch a man as</hi> Timothy <hi>who had faith already, yet they could no
way be profitable nor uſeful to one that had not faith, or did not believe
them to be the Word of God; for Faith comes by hearing, not by
reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Firſt, If the Scriptures are not a Guide to
them that believe not, why do the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> ſay that the reaſon
why Jews and Hereticks do not finde Chriſt to be their King, Lord, Life, and
Saviour, is, becauſe they did not <pb n="37" facs="tcp:109129:26"/>ſearch the Scriptures
deeply. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you will not ſay, that Jews and Hereticks are Believers, and
you ſay, they are no guide to Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; why then do the
<hi>Rhemiſts</hi> ſay, Chriſt reprehended them for not fearching the
Scriptures deeply? To what purpoſe then are Jews and Hereticks blamed for not
ſearching the Scriptures deeply, if the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures had been (as you ſay)
no way profitable to them? but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you ſay, they are not profitable to
them that do not believe them to be the word of God. Suppoſe this were
granted (which cannot be proved) doth it not follow that your Roman Church (by
the ſame reaſon) is no way profitable, no way a Judge, nor an infallible
Guide to any that do not believe her to be ſo: and by the ſame reaſon an
Atheiſt may ſay All gods providences are no monitors to him, All his
judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are no examples to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <pb n="38" facs="tcp:109129:27"/>cauſe he
doth not believe there is a God: Is not this as good Logick, as to ſay the
Scriptures are no way profitable to them that do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them to be the
Word of God.</p>
            <p>You proceed to give another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why this Scripture 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. is not a proof for what is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>becauſe then
if the Scriptures more ſolely ſufficient which</hi> Timothy <hi>knew from a
child (they being but the Scriptures of the Old
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt) it would follow that Christ, and the Now Teſtament,
and the Sacraments, and the Apoſtles, are at leaſt not
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, if by the Scriptures ſole ſufficiency, (you mean)
that they are ſufficient to bring men to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without Faith,
Repentance, and Obedience, then this is a Puppit of your own (as you Phraſe
it) for where is there any Proteſtant of that mind; therefore you do but bark
againſt the Moon.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:109129:27"/>
            <p>But we ſay they are ſolely ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to direct us to
thoſe ways by which we may obtain ſalvation. But then (ſay you) <hi>What
needed Chriſt and the Apostles, and the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if the
Scriptures</hi> Timothy <hi>had learned (which were thoſe of the Old
Teſtament) were ſufficient?</hi> But then I anſwer as before, if Chriſt
and the Apoſtles were ſolely ſufficient, what need is there of your Pope
and Council? So that by this Argument you either make Chriſt and his
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles not ſolely ſufficient; or if they were, then what need this
waſte of a General Council? But you may ſay, that a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil was to
direct people in ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages. So were the Scriptures much rather, for
whatever was written aforetime was written for our Learning, upon whom the ends
of the World are come.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, you ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 15. <hi>The word</hi>
All <hi>Scripture muſt either ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <pb n="40" facs="tcp:109129:28"/>every
Scripture, as the Original word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
ought to be rendred, or</hi> All <hi>Scriptures that ever were; or</hi> All
<hi>Scriptures that were when this Text was written; or</hi> All <hi>that we
now have. If it be to be underſtood of every Scripture (or any Scripture)
then you ſay it doth prove too much, becauſe then all the Scriptures ſave
one Book, are uſeleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though what hath been ſaid doth ſufficiently anſwer this
innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore I might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed from anſwering any
farther: yet becauſe you intimate a farther proof of what you now urge, I
ſhall therefore when I meet with it give a further Anſwer.</p>
            <p>You come in the 16 <hi>page</hi> to tell your Reader, <hi>That you
met with no Arguments for the ſole ſufficiency of Scripture among thoſe
that were uſually urged, and therefore you reſolved to ſee what could be
ſaid againſt this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon General opinion of all who oppoſe the Church
of</hi> Rome, <hi>why the Scriptures <pb n="41" facs="tcp:109129:28"/>could not be this Rule
and Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>you have not met with any Arguments to prove the
ſole ſufficiency of Scripture to be our guide;</hi> but it was becauſe
you did not make a deep &amp; diligent ſearch into them, which is the
reaſon (as your <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> ſay) Hereticks never find the Truth.
But why do you beguile your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Reader with this word, <hi>(viz.) That the
Scriptures are not a</hi> SOLE <hi>Guide?</hi> thereby to let him think that
you allow them in ſome ſenſe to be a guide; when indeed your following
Arguments do manifeſtly declare that you would not have them to be any guide
at all.</p>
            <p>Your firſt Reaſon why the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are not a Guide is,
<hi>becauſe they do not anſwer the end,</hi> (viz.) <hi>the reconciling
differences: for thoſe who pretend most to conſult the Scriptures, do
moſt of all diſagree in matters of faith; and interpreting the
Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:109129:29"/>
            <p>To this I anſwer, Firſt, May not a Heathen or a Jew alledge
the ſame Argument againſt Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf, and ſay that the
Chriſtian Religion is no ſafe way to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe of the
differences that are among the Profeſſors of it?</p>
            <p n="2">2 May it not be ſaid that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves
were no certain Guides, becauſe they had diviſions and contentions among
them? and that they had, appears by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of St. <hi>Paul</hi>
himſelf, <hi>Rom</hi> 16.17. <hi>Mark them that cauſe diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and
offences contrary to the doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. And the ſame Apoſtle tells
the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.
<hi>That there was among them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyings, ſtrife, and contention, ſome
holding of</hi> Paul, <hi>and ſome of</hi> Apollo, <hi>ſome of</hi> Cephas.
Nay, he further tells them, <hi>there must be Hereſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, that they
that are approved, might be made manifeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 May it not as well be ſaid of <pb n="43" facs="tcp:109129:29"/>the
Church of the Jews (which, you ſay, were infallible) that they were no Guide,
or at leaſt, no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Guide, becauſe there were dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and
contentions among them, as there was between the <hi>Phariſees, Sadduces</hi>
and <hi>Eſſavaus;</hi> it is ſaid that the <hi>Sadduces</hi> denied the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, Angels, and Spirit: as you ſay the Scriptures are no Guide
to true faith, becauſe men differ and and diſagree in matters of Faith:
But,</p>
            <p n="4">4 May you not as well ſay that Chriſt is not the Saviour
of the World, and that he came not into the World to the end that the World
might be ſaved, becauſe it doth not appear that all ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:
as, ſay the Scriptures are no Guide to end Controverſies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all
Controverſies are not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p n="5">5 May you not as well infer that the grace of God doth not
teach <pb n="44" facs="tcp:109129:30"/>men to deny ungodlineſs, becauſe ſome turn the
grace of God into wantonneſs: as ſay the Scriptures are no ſure Guide to
faith and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, becauſe many wreſt them to their own
deſtruction?</p>
            <p n="6">6 May you not as well ſay, that the Primitive Church were
no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Guide to true faith, becauſe they had diſagreements and
conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among them: as the ſtrife between the Eaſtern and Weſtern
Churches about the keeping of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and they excommunicating one another?
And the Queſtion of Re-baptizing bred the like differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between the
Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Weſtern Biſhops of one Party, and
<hi>Cyprian, Dionyſius,</hi> and <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milianus,</hi> with, moſt of the
Eaſtern Biſhops of the other Party, <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 5.
<hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Cyp. Ep.</hi> 74, 75.
<hi>Soc. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Soc. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 21. I
ſay, may not one more truly infer theſe were no Guides, <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109129:30"/>becauſe they had diſſentions and diviſions among them: as you
may ſay the Scriptures are not a Guide, becauſe of the differences that are
amongſt Proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And laſtly, May I not infer as well from the like
Premiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is and hath been diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences among the
now-pretended Catholicks, as I have already ſhewn, that therefore their
Church is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Guide: as you may ſay the men that conſult
Scriptures do not agree among themſelves, therefore the Scriptures are not
the Guide.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond Reaſon followeth in the 17 <hi>pag.</hi> which is
but the ſame in effect with the firſt, therefore the former Anſwer may
ſuffice; onely you tell us a ſtory of an <hi>Arian,</hi> or, (as the
<hi>Queſtion of Queſtions</hi> hath it) an <hi>Arian Cobler;</hi> how that
if you were to diſpute with him about the Deity of Chriſt from
<hi>Job.</hi> 10.30. <hi>I and my Father are one;</hi> by this Text 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109129:31"/>(you ſay) you ſhould think you had proved the
Queſtion. But then (you ſay) your <hi>Arian</hi> would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare this Text
with <hi>john</hi> 17.21. where Chriſt prayeth to his Father, that his
Diſciples might be all one thing, <hi>as thou (Father) are in me, and I in
thee.</hi> But if you ſhould urge the <hi>Arian</hi> further, and tell him
the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> gave the ſame Interpretation which you do: (you
ſay) the <hi>Arian</hi> would anſwer as the Proteſtants generally do,
that they have a worthy eſteem of Councils, as far as they agree with the
Word of God; but where they diſagree, in that he muſt contradict them
all.</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, (ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the contraverſie
between the <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Athanaſians,</hi> as not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within
the verge of our preſent queſtion) that if the <hi>Arian</hi> Cobler had
been as Orthodox in all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Opinions, as he is in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109129:31"/>about the Holy Scriptures, and Councels <hi>(viz.)</hi> to
think reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Councels, and agree with them, as far as they agree with
the World of Truth: I ſay, if this had been all this <hi>Arian</hi> Coblers
Errour, I ſhould have judged him a better Chriſtian then a <hi>Roman</hi>
Shoo-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, or the Catholick Collier, who could ſay no more for himſelf,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tempted by the Devil at the point of death, what his faith was?
Anſwered, I believe, and dye in the faith of Chriſts Church: Being again
demanded what the Faith of Chriſts Church was? Anſwered, The faith that I
believe in: See Apology Tranſlated by <hi>Staplet. p.</hi> 53.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>That you can urge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an</hi> Arian
<hi>the Authority of the Councel of</hi> Nice, <hi>and their Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
the Scripture, by which they In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly decide the controverſie; And here
you think you have a more certaine <pb n="48" facs="tcp:109129:32"/>guide and ground of your
Faith then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe they adhere to private ſpirits, and private
judgements up on the Scriptures; whereas you adhere to general
Councel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which, I Anſwer, Firſt, Doe you think that General Councels
did ſpeak and teach in more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Speech, and that they utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
words leſs ſubject to be wreſted by wrong interpretations, then the words
of the Prophets and Apoſtles were, who ſpake as they were inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by
the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, How do you know that you have the true ſenſe and
meaning of the Councels determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, ſince their Decrees are as lyable,
if not more lyable to miſ-interpretations then the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this queſtion is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you did not hear
them your ſelf, and if you had heard them, you might have miſ-underſtood
them, <pb n="49" facs="tcp:109129:32"/>but if you ſay you have read the Councels and ſo
came to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: I do further demand how you do believe by a Divine Faith,
that you do not miſ-underſtand the Councels in what you read, and ſo
collect a falſe ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you ſhall ſay you have a Prieſt to teach you the
ſenſe of the Councels, by which you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what Doctrines are
Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and what Expoſitions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are true, and what are falſe
then I demand.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, How do you believe with a Divine Faith, that what this
private Prieſt teacheth is according to the Infallible Doctrine of the
Church, ſince he is a Man, and may err, and ſo teach his own private
O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, for the Infallible Doctrine of the Church.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Whether you may not be more ſubject to
miſ-underſtand the Scriptures, either by the errour <pb n="50" facs="tcp:109129:33"/>of
the Prieſt in Preaching, or the frailty of your underſtanding in hearing,
then others are in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Holy Scriptures: And if ſo, why
ſhould you ſay the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are no guide, becauſe they may be
miſ-interpreted? For ſhame forbear to blame the uſe of a thing becauſe
of the abuſe of it: What if ſome are to blame, in that they have wreſted
the Scriptures to ſerve their own intereſts; Are not you more to blame to
wound theſe men through the ſides of the Scripture? What if (as one well
obſerves) <hi>That ſome are blind, and miſs their way, and others are
drunk, and stagger out of it: Muſt we all conſpire to wiſh the Sun out of
the Firmament, that we might follow a Will with a Wiſp?</hi> And yet this is
your kind of reaſoning, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome are perverſe and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
and others are full of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, prejudice, and corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by
which they cannot perfectly <pb n="51" facs="tcp:109129:33"/>and infallibly judge of every
truth, that is contained in the Scripture; therefore they muſt throw away the
bleſſed word of God from being their rule and guide.</p>
            <p>You proceed in <hi>p.</hi> 18. and tell us, <hi>That the third
Reaſon which you thought was forcible, was, that thoſe who are thus far for
ſole Scripture, do not ſay that one, or any particular number of the Books
of Scripture, but all Scriptures written by inſpiration of God do, being
joyned together make up this Rule and Judge; Hence</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you
concluded that if any of theſe Books were lost, this Rule was not perfect;
Now that many of theſe Books were loſt</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
from thoſe that remain,</hi> Num. 21.14. <hi>The Book of the Wars of the Lord
(and this</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is loſt.) It is ſaid of</hi> Solomon, 1
King. 4.3, 2. <hi>that he ſpoke</hi> 3000 <hi>Proverbs, and his Songs
were</hi> 1000 <hi>and</hi> 5; <hi>You conceive</hi> (you ſay) <hi>that upon
a juſt reckoning ſome of theſe will be wanting: We finde named,</hi> 
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:109129:34"/>2 Chron. 9.29. <hi>The Book of</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <hi>the
Prophet, the Propheſie of</hi> Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah, <hi>and the Viſions of</hi> Iddo;
(<hi>theſe</hi> (you ſay) <hi>are loſt) as alſo thoſe named,</hi> 1
Chron. 29.29. <hi>The Book of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, <hi>the Book of</hi> Nathan,
<hi>the Book of</hi> Goda, <hi>and it is clear from</hi> Mat. 27.9. <hi>That
part of</hi> Jeremy <hi>is loſt; So alſo from</hi> Mat. 2.23. <hi>Where it
was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told that Christ ſhould be called a</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaren; <hi>and</hi> 1
Cor. 5.9. <hi>Tells us that the Epistle which our Canon calls St.</hi> Pauls
<hi>Firſt Epiſtle was not truly his firſt; for there he ſayeth, I wrote
to you in an Epistle, not to keep company with Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catours: St.</hi> Paul
<hi>alſo wrote an Epiſtle from</hi> Laodicea, <hi>and yet</hi> (you ſay)
<hi>you do not finde this Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer hereunto I cannot but take notice that you ſay you
THOUGHT this Anſwer was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible; but where was your Mother that ſhe did
not inable you to ſay, you were SURE it was forcible.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:109129:34"/>
            <p>But let us ſee wherein this force lyeth; you ſay,
<hi>Proteſtants do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a certain number of Books to be their guide;
but all the Scriptures written by Inſpiration from God, make up this Rule and
Guide; and many of theſe Books are loſt, therefore this Rule is not
perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Firſt, That the Law of the Lord is perfect, and
every word of God is pure; and therefore there can be no imperfections in the
word of God: but</p>
            <p>Secondly, How doth it appear that any of thoſe Books which (you
ſay) were loſt, had a Divine Image and Superſcription upon them; or that
they that did write them we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt in the writing of thoſe particular Books? For
it is very poſſible that they wrote many things upon particular
occaſions, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> wrote to <hi>Ephraim;</hi> and that
ſometimes their writings were of no more inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <pb n="54" facs="tcp:109129:35"/>from Heaven, then <hi>Davids</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were that he ſent to
<hi>Joab</hi> by <hi>Uriah,</hi> or then <hi>Peters</hi> practiſe for which
<hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to the face: But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What Infallible reaſon have you to prove that theſe
ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings recited out of theſe Scriptures may not refer to the Books of
<hi>Samuel</hi> and the <hi>Kings</hi> which we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, rather then to
any Books that are loſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, How do you know that thoſe writings (however the
Pen-men were inſpired) were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by God for the perpetual uſe of his
Church in all Ages.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, How do you Infallibly know, that all the Canons or your
Church, even of thoſe which (you ſay) are neceſſary to Salvation are
preſerved, and that ſome very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial things are not loſt.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If you ſay there is none loſt, then whether you do
not make <pb n="55" facs="tcp:109129:35"/>God in his wiſe providence more carefull to
preſerve intire and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maimed the Canons of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, then he hath been
to preſerve the Writings of his Holy Prophets, and Apoſtles; And if you
ſuppoſe any of the Decrees of your Councels hath been loſt or maimed,
then how do you know Infallibly, whether ſome that are loſt, are not as
material as thoſe you have? Thus the edge of your ſword is turned
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſelf: But</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If any of the Books of the Old Teſtament were loſt,
that were by God intended for the perpetual uſe of that Church to whom his
Oracles were committed, how then can you ſay that the Church of the Old
Teſtament was infallible, ſince ſhe failed in that truſt that was
committed to her, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the keeping of the Scripture? And if this was
not a failing in her, in that ſhe loſt part of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109129:36"/>then ſhe had not failed, if ſhe had loſt all; and
then it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Scriptures are ſo far from being a ſole Guide,
that they are no guide at all, for if they are a guide, and a directer in any
ſenſe, or if they are of any divine uſe, then it muſt be an errour
either of ignorance, or wilfullneſſe, to ſuffer them to be loſt or
maimed.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, <hi>Whereas you ſay, that the Epiſtle of St.</hi>
Paul <hi>which your Canon calls the firſt to the</hi> Corinthians <hi>was
not</hi> TRULY <hi>his firſt:</hi> I Anſwer then, your Canon doth falſely
call it the firſt, and then how ſhall we believe when your Canons are true?
You had beſt tell your Mother ſhe lyes as ſoon as you can ſpeak, and
then ſhew a reaſon for it, by telling her <hi>That St.</hi> Paul
<hi>ſaith, he writ to the</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians <hi>an Epiſtle before:</hi>
Ergo, <hi>there is an Epiſtle before that which your Canon calls the
firſt:</hi> But <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> underſtands it of the words going 
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109129:36"/>before, wherein he had charged them to deliver the
inceſtious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Satan, and to purge out the old leaven.</p>
            <p>And that you may ſee how little cauſe you have to enveigh
againſt Proteſtants for their private doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and uncertain expounding
of Scriptures; Let me give you the expoſition of a whole Colledge of
Catholicks upon this very Text un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der debate: <hi>Either</hi> (ſay they)
<hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>means this Epistle in the words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or ſome other:
See the Rhemiſts marginall Note upon the place.</hi> Surely this is
infallible indeed; it is either this or ſome other: At this rate of
Infallibility any private ſpirit ſhall interpret Scriptures all day long,
<hi>(viz.)</hi> either this is the ſenſe, or ſome other.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, and Laſtly, If any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Scripture be loſt will
not this redound to the prejudice of the Romane Church: Since they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109129:37"/>that they only are the Church, and that the Church is the
keeper of Divine Truths, and that they have been the conſervatours of the
Scriptures to poſterity. Now if any Books be loſt (as you ſay there is)
how have they infallibly kept what (they ſay) was long ſince committed to
their truſt? Thus you deſperatly venture to wound the reputation of the
Scriptures, though you make the Sword, by which you do it, to paſs through
the reins of your darling infallibility.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 19. you come to a Fourth Reaſon, <hi>Why the
Scriptures cannot be a guide to conveigh Divine and Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible faith to all;
and that is, becauſe they cannot be underſtood by all, nay,</hi> (you
ſay) <hi>they are very ſubject to be miſ-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, if we will
believe the</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16. <hi>Where ſpeaking of St.</hi> Pauls
<hi>Epistles,</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>there were ſome things hard to be
underſtood, which they that are unlearned, and unſtable wreſt as 
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109129:37"/>they do alſo the other Scriptures to their own
deſtruction. It is in vain</hi> (you ſay) <hi>to urge that the Scriptures
are plain and eaſie in fundamentals, and in what concerns ſalvation; for we
have here a plain teſtimony that they are wreſted to their own
destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; therefore they cannot be a ſafe rule, nor any rule at all to
the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this Argument be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered already, yet I anſwer
fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the words of a learned man, <hi>That if the Scriptures are ſo
hard to be underſtood, and the Pope can infallibly interpret them, what a
madneſs and childiſhneſs is it for the Catholicks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to lie
ſwaggering and contending with one another, before all the world with
fallible mediums, about the ſenſe of Scripture, when they have one among
them that infallibly can interpret them, and that with ſuch Authority, as all
men are bound to reſt in, and contend no further?</hi> And the further
miſchief <pb n="60" facs="tcp:109129:38"/>of it is, that of all the reſt, this man is
always ſilent as to expoſition of Scripture, who alone is able to part the
fray. Now methinks this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a great want of good nature, that the Pope can
ſee his Children ſo fiercely wrangle about the ſenſe of Scripture, and
yet will not give out the infallible meaning of every place, and ſo ſtint
the ſtrife among them, ſeeing he can do it if he will.</p>
            <p>But again, how doth it follow, that becauſe the Scriptures are
hard to be underſtood, and are by ſome wreſted to their damnation, that
therefore they are either no Guides at all, or at the beſt but uncertain
ones. Pray let me ask you a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or two, May you not as well ſay that
Chriſt was no infallible Guide, becauſe many of his words were wreſted by
the Jews to their deſtruction? as that of his deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Temple and
building it in three days? <hi>Job.</hi> 2.19. And did not <pb n="61" facs="tcp:109129:38"/>they wreſt his words to their own deſtruction, when Chriſt
ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.64, 65. that he was the Son of God, and they thereupon
ſaid he had ſpoken blaſphemy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needed no other witneſs
againſt him: and likewiſe they ſaid, he blaſphemed when he told the man
that was ſick of the Palſie, that his ſins were forgiven. So that
ſpeech of Chriſt was hard to be underſtood to learned <hi>Nicodemus,
Job.</hi> 3. <hi>Except a man be born again he cannot enter into the Kingdom of
God.</hi> Doth it follow from hence that Chriſt was not an infallible
Guide?</p>
            <p>Again are the Canons and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of General Councils more
ſecure from being miſinterpreted then the Scriptures; or do they uſe more
plainneſs of ſpeech then the Spirit of God uſed in the Scriptures, or is
nothing that they determine of neceſſity to ſalvation? If ſo, then why
may not their words <pb n="62" facs="tcp:109129:39"/>be wreſted to the deſtruction of
thoſe that are unlearned or unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as well (or rather as ill) as the
Scriptures. And if ſo, I demand whether this be not as good, nay a better
Argument againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>(viz.)</hi> ſome wreſt the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and definitions of the Church to their deſtruction; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Church
is not an infallible Guide to all, nor indeed any Guide to the ignorant, which
are the greateſt part of mankind? Is not this the ſame (if not a better)
argument, then to ſay, the unlearned wreſt the Scriptures to their own
deſtruction; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Scriptures are not an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Guide to
all, nor any Guide at all to the ignorant.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider your 5 Reaſon, which is, <hi>That if
the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures be a Guide, Rule, and Judge, it must onely be meant of their
true Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and Authentick Writings, and not of corrupted Copies; and
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb n="63" facs="tcp:109129:39"/>if we have not the true Originals, our rule is
imperfect.</hi> And again <hi>pag.</hi> 20. you ſay, <hi>If we had the
Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, it would be hard to find a man that doth ſo infallibly
underſtand the Originals, as to give us a true tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This you
endeavour to prove out of ſeveral Proteſtant Writers, <hi>pag.</hi> 20.
<hi>&amp;</hi> 21. <hi>(viz.) That we have not the Originals themſelves, nor
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Tranſlations, and therefore the Scriptures are not an infallible
Guide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That though what hath been ſpoken already
might ſuffice to this Argument, yet to make full meaſure running over, let
me add, that this very Objection lieth with the like force againſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
Councils. For, firſt, how do you know with a divine certitude, that you have
the true Original and Authentick Writings, wherein thoſe Decrees were
contained? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, How do you know with a <pb n="64" facs="tcp:109129:40"/>divine
certitude, whether the Scribe that committed them to Writing was an honeſt
man or not? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, How do you know with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine certitude, that theſe
Councils, Decrees, and Canons, are truly and infallibly tranſlated, ſince
they were written in a Language that I know not. If you ſay I have them
tranſlated by private Doctors, then I query if private Doctors are
infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible? If they are, what need is there of a Pope, or a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil?
If they are fallible, why may they not fail, when they tell me they have
faithfully interpreted and tranſlated the ſenſe of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Fathers?
But if they being private perſons can give the true ſenſe of Councils and
Fathers, why may not men of the ſame ability for Learning and Piety give as
perfect a Tranſlation, and as infallible an Interpretation of the Scriptures
of the Apoſtles and Prophets? So that <pb n="65" facs="tcp:109129:40"/>the Argument cuts
as much with one edge as the other. <hi>If the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures be guide and rule,
it muſt be meant of Authentical and Original Writings, or of infallible
Tranſlations of them into ſeveral Languages, &amp;c.</hi> ſay you. In
like manner I ſay, if the Decrees of General Councils are infallible, it
muſt be underſtood of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and authentick writings where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
thoſe Decrees are contained, or of infallible Tranſlations of them into
ſeveral Languages, ſince they were not given out in a Language that the
Common people under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Now none will ſwear (to uſe your own words,
<hi>pag.</hi> 20.) that theſe are the Originals of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of thoſe
Councils, ſome of them being more then a thouſand years old. Neither will
any ſwear that the Tranſlations of theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees agree with their
Originals: <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Decrees and Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Councils cannot be
an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable <pb n="66" facs="tcp:109129:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>and infallible Guide to true
faith.</p>
            <p>Thus you make people believe that if they come to your Church,
they ſhall have every thing certain; but I do demand (if any ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
your advice) how they ſhall be thus aſſured, ſince your Church hath
been ſo palpably negligent, as to ſuffer whole Books to be loſt, and to
ſuffer the Originals of thoſe that remain, to be corrupted, and alſo to
ſuffer infinite variety of reading to come into them; by which you ſay,
<hi>It cannot be diſcerned infallibly which is the true reading, and which is
the falſe.</hi> And whereas you ſay, <hi>That we are ſo far from having
St.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews <hi>Original, that we know not what Language it was writ in;
or whether he who tranſtated it into Greek was an honeſt man or
not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, If your Church were (as you pretend) the ſole Keeper
of the Scriptures, they are worthy <pb n="67" facs="tcp:109129:41"/>to die (as
<hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Abner</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they kept their Maſter no
better. Are they the Church to which no unfaithfulneſs can have acceſs,
when they have loſt the Original of St. <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpel? Theſe
are worſe then the unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant; for in the day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, though
he did not improve his Talent, yet he did not loſe it; but could ſay to his
Maſter, take that which is thine own. But you that have been entruſted with
the heavenly treaſure of ſacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, it ſeems, cannot acquit your
ſelves at this rate; for you have loſt the Original, and cannot tell
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Tranſlation that you have was done by an honeſt Man or a
Knave.</p>
            <p>But further, If this be true, what becomes of that Text which you
cite, as the firſt-born of your ſtrength, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. upon which
you found your Churches infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <pb n="68" facs="tcp:109129:42"/>for if one ask you,
how you prove the Church infallible? you ſay by that Text, <hi>Upon this Rock
I will build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt
it.</hi> But how do you prove it from this Text? if (as you ſay) the Original
is loſt, and you cannot tell whether he that tranſlated it into the Greek
was an honeſt man or no?</p>
            <p>You come now, <hi>pag.</hi> 22. to a ſixth Reaſon, which is
but the ſame in effect with the former, <hi>(viz.) That whatſoever is a
ſufficient rule, muſt be plain and clear in all neceſſary points: the
Scriptures</hi> (you ſay) <hi>are not plain and clear in all neceſſary
points; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore &amp;c.</hi> This is the ſum of your Argument, and for
this you give divers inſtances of things neceſſary to ſalvation, that
are not ſet down in Scripture, The firſt is, in <hi>pag.</hi> 22.23. That
<hi>it is not ſet down in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture what a Sacrament is, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there
be, or whether there be any or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:109129:42"/>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That you ſtrive about words; for it is not
neceſſary to ſalvation to believe that thoſe inſtitutions ſhould be
called Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are uſually ſo called; and if it were, then it
would be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that we ſhould know what and how many Inſtitutions
ſhould be ſo denominated: but it ſufficeth that thoſe Inſtitutions
which we call Sacraments, are plainly ſet down in Scripture, together with
the perſons who ſhould obſerve them, and the manner how they ſhould be
obſerved.</p>
            <p>You come to a ſecond thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be believed that is
not in Scripture; namely, <hi>That all the Books of the Holy Scriptures be the
word of God.</hi> This ſay is not abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation;
for it may be poſſible for one to believe all the matter of the Bible to be
the Truth of God, and thereupon be ſaved, who may yet doubt, whether every 
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109129:43"/>one of the Pen-men did write by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration. And again,
When it is ſaid and believed that all the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Objects of Faith, and
thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Verities which Chriſt revealed to his Apoſtles, and they to
the Churches, are laid down in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. It is manifeſt that the
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures themſelves are excepted, they being not received as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial
objects of our faith, but as the means of conveying them unto us: and if a man
did believe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſalvation contained in the Scripture, it
ſhould not hinder his ſalvation, though he knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there was any
Scripture or no?</p>
            <p>Again, Many of thoſe whom you Canonize, did not allow of ſome
part of the Scriptures; and many whole Churches differed about the Authority of
ſome Books; which Churches muſt all be damned, if the believing thoſe
Books had been ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:109129:43"/>
            <p>You proceed and ſay in the third place, <hi>That it is
neceſſary to ſalvation to believe the Scriptures to be the Word of God,
but this</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is not plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet down in Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer as before, This belief cannot be neceſſary, where
the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are not propoſed; for God doth not require men to believe
upon pain of Damnation, when he hath not given means in order therunto.</p>
            <p>But 2. Whoever ſhall conſult the excellent precepts, the
glorious promiſes, together with that great Spirit of Holineſs and
Self-denial that is contained in the Scriptures, muſt needs ſay, that they
have the image and ſuperſcription of heaven upon them; and from thence be
as certainly perſwaded that God was the Author of them, as if it had been
written with the beam of the Sun, that ſo many Books are the Word of God:
nay, and more certain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <pb n="72" facs="tcp:109129:44"/>
               <hi>That</hi> one
ſentence might ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner have been expunged, or defaced out of the Scriptures
then that Spirit of Light and Truth which breaths in the faces and
conſciences of men, from all the quarters of them.</p>
            <p>Your other inſtances that follow, are ſuch as we have either
taken notice of already, or elſe they are ſuch that are not neceſſary
to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore are impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alledged to weaken the
guidance and conduct of the Scripture in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that bleſſed end. But
ſince you are ſo able to lay ſtumbling blocks in the way of the
Scriptures, that thereby men might ſtumble and fall, let me ſee if you are
as able to remove ſome ſtumbling blocks that lieth in the way to your
infallible Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Is not the Sacrament of Pennance, as your Church
teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, neceſſary to ſalvation?</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, How can you be <pb n="73" facs="tcp:109129:44"/>infallible that
this Sacrament is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by a true Prieſt? for if it were not done by
a true Prieſt, then it is ineffectual, and ſo you muſt die without
abſolution, or elſe you muſt grant that others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide a lawful
Prieſt may remit ſins. But if none can do it but a lawful Prieſt:</p>
            <p>Then Thirdly, How ſhall you be infallible of thoſe things that
are neceſſary to make a true Prieſt? as firſt, that he was lawfully
baptized with due matter and due form of words; and that the Biſhop which
Ordained him a Prieſt, did Ordain him compleatly, with due matter, form, and
intention? You muſt know that the Biſhop that made him a Prieſt, was a
Prieſt himſelf. But ſuppoſe theſe doubts were aſſayled, which
cannot be; and that you are certain, he that is to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve you were a true
Prieſt; yet ſtill the doubt will remain, whether <pb n="74" facs="tcp:109129:45"/>he
will do you that good he can? and whether he will pronounce the words of
abſolution with an intent to abſolve you? For perhaps he may bear you
ſome ſecret grudge, and project your damnation for a revenge. He may, for
ought you know, be a ſecret Jew, or Anti-Trinitarian, and ſo far from
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending your forgiveneſs of ſins, and ſalvation by this Sacrament,
that in his heart he laughs at all theſe things, and thinks ſin nothing,
and ſalvation but a word. All theſe doubts muſt be clearly reſolved
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can (upon your Roman Catholick grounds) aſſure your ſelf that
this man that abſolveth you is a true Prieſt, and that he giveth you true
and effectual abſolution; or elſe when you have done all this for your
ſalvation, you may have the ill luck to be damned; which makes ſalvation a
matter of chance and not of choice; and if ſo, what are you 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109129:45"/>the nearer for being a member of a pretended infallible
Church. Much more to this purpoſe might be ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and yet you cry out, that
the Salvation of Proteſtants relies upon fallible and uncertain grounds.
Whoever would be further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in this matter, I ſhall deſire him to
read that learned Treatiſe of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> Intituled, <hi>The
Religion of Protestants, a ſafe way to Salvation.</hi> Your next inſtance
is, <hi>The Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that ſeems to appear in Scriptures, which</hi>
(you ſay) <hi>argues them to ſeem untrue,</hi> and for this you inſtance,
2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.26. compared with 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.5. and <hi>Mat.</hi>
1.17. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Luke</hi> 3.35, 36. <hi>which places</hi> (you ſay)
<hi>ſeem to contradict each other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer Firſt, If they are but ſeeming contradictions, then
they do not weaken the reputation of Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:109129:46"/>
            <p>Secondly, The reſolving thoſe ſeeming contradictions are not
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation, becauſe it is not neceſſary to ſalvation
to know when <hi>Ahazia</hi> began to Reign, not whether there were 41 or 42
Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and therefore
thoſe Objections weaken not the guidance of the Scriptures in all things
neceſſary to ſalvation, which is the thing in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, why doth your Church put her candle under a
Buſhel, why doth not ſhe ſet forth an infallible tranſlation of the
Bible? For it may be thoſe ſeeming contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in thoſe fore-cited
places was occaſioned by the errour of the Scribe, or the errour of the
Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatour. But hath not greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences attended the keeping the
Canons of your Church? If they have not, how comes it to paſs that there is
contradictions in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <pb n="77" facs="tcp:109129:46"/>and none in Councils? It
ſeems your Church hath faithfully preſerved all things uncorrupted for the
benefit of poſterity, but the word of God. You proceed, <hi>pag.</hi> 25. to
a ſeventh Reaſon, Why <hi>the Scriptures are not a ſole guide, becauſe
then they would have been ſo in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes; and if they had, then
the Authority of the Apoſtles</hi> (you ſay) <hi>muſt have ceaſed ſo
ſoon as they had made an end of writing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That it doth not follow that the opinion of the
Scriptures being the ſole guide, ſhould exclude the Apoſtles from being
guides when they were living.</p>
            <p>May not a Man as well ſay, that <hi>Peters</hi> being the ſole
head of the Church (as you pretend) did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Chriſt (that gave him his
Authority) from being head while he was yet living on the Earth; and that a man
that directs and ſolely guides you by Epiſtles, how to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109129:47"/>your affairs, ſhould thereby ceaſe to be a guide if he
were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with you, or that he ſhould thereby be rendred unable to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve any doubtfull word in that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. No more doth it follow, that
the Scriptures being held to be the ſole guide, ſhould exclude the Pen-men
from either being guides, or giving an infallible interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own
words, while they were yet alive. But what is all this to the Romane Church
being an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible guide? The Apoſtles might be guides to the Churches
while they lived, both by their words and writings; But ſince they are
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, we know no furer guide then their words, to which to do well to
take heed, as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe other things that you ſay follow in probability
upon the Scriptures being our guide; I ſhall ſay nothing to them, becauſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109129:47"/>they are but probable conjectures of your own brain.</p>
            <p>Your laſt reaſon which you urge, why the Scripture is not a
ſole Judge, is, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (you ſay) <hi>in effect it is to make it
no judge at all, but to make every man and woman to be their own judge, to take
upon them to read and understand them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May you not as well ſay, that your Church is not the judge,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every man and woman muſt judge for themſelves, whether ſhe be
ſo or no, before they joyne in Communion with her: As ſay the Scriptures
are not ſo, becauſe a man muſt judge for himſelf, whether he rightly
underſtand it or no?</p>
            <p>Is there not as great a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in the World, which is the
true Church among all the pretenders to it, as there is, which is the right
ſenſe of Scriptures among the various readings and interpretations
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Now how doth a mans judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="80" facs="tcp:109129:48"/>for himſelf, after
he hath weighed Arguments and compared Text with Text render the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to
be no guide, any more then your hearing and examining all the Arguments and
Reaſons which are alledged for the True Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all pretenders to it
and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward according to your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judge which is true, renders
your ſelf, and not your Church the true guide. And yet this is your Argument,
<hi>Every man judgeth for himſelf which is the true ſenſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the
Scriptures are in themſelves no judge at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the cloſe of this Argument, <hi>p.</hi> 26. You conclude,
<hi>That if God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſouls of Men, he would have provided ſome ſure
means by which they might have been aſſured of the true faith,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>without leaving them to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be interpreted by each one, as
he thinks beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:109129:48"/>
            <p>May not I reply as before, That if God loved the ſouls of men,
he would have left them ſome ſure means to finde the True Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the
many falſe pretenders to it, and not have left it to themſelves to chooſe
which Church in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Judgement they ſhall think is the true
one.</p>
            <p>Having done with your negative poſitions, viz. <hi>That the
private ſpirit, Reaſon, and Scripture is not the ſole Judge;</hi> you
come to infer from the whole, <hi>That the Catholick Church is this judge, and
that God had alwayes ſuch a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This you endeavour to make good by ſaying, <hi>God had ſuch a
Church Two Thouſand Years before any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was written;</hi> And to
demonſtrate this you ſay; <hi>Circumciſion was brought in by</hi>
Abraham, <hi>and practiſed by the Church without Scripture to try it by,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:109129:49"/>
            <p>I Anſwer firſt, If the Pope will bring in any new Law or Canon
with that Authority as <hi>Abraham</hi> brought in Circumciſion, we will
believe him without a Council, or deſiring him to prove it by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
But</p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſeems here is ſome other Rule and Guide beſide
Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Scripture, the private Spirit, and the Church; for here is no
Council to decree Circumciſion, nor private ſpirit to ſuggeſt it, nor
reaſon to contrive it; But here is God appearing to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and
commanding it by an immediate voice from Heaven; So that this was Gods way of
guiding his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then, and not by General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and of this opinion is
<hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome Hom.</hi> 1. in <hi>Mat.</hi> who conceives <hi>God might
uſe other means;</hi> and this agrees with that ſaying, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1.
God in ſundry times, and in diverſe manners ſpake to our Fathers by the
Prophets.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:109129:49"/>
            <p>Laſtly, If the Scriptures are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to many exceptions (as you
ſay) by which they are rendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being our infallible Guide, then
I demand how you know what was tranſacted in the World the firſt 2000
Years, and whether there was any Church at all in thoſe times. If you ſay
you are by the Hyſtory of the Scriptures guided to believe what was done 2000
Years before the firſt Pen-man was born; I demand how you can believe this,
ſince they are ſo fallibly and ſubject to ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions as you
ſay? But further, may I not with more certitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what
<hi>Moſes</hi> and all the Pen-men of Holy Scriptures writ of things they
were eye-witneſſes of, then you can be of what <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the
firſt 2000 Years that were expired before he was born?</p>
            <p>You come in <hi>pag.</hi> 27 to a ſecond Argument, Namely,
<hi>That the Church <pb n="84" facs="tcp:109129:50"/>of the Jews, were ſo the Jews,</hi>
(I ſuppoſe you mean an infallible guide) <hi>after the Scriptures were
written;</hi> and for this purpoſe you cite, Deut. 17.8. <hi>The man that
will do preſumptiouſly, and will not hearken to the voice of the Prieſt
or unto the Judge that man ſhall dye.</hi> I anſwer, The Scripture ſaith,
<hi>Pro.</hi> 16.10. A divine ſentence is in the lips of the King his mouth
tranſgreſſeth not in judgement; Doth it follow from hence, that all Kings
are infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible in their judgments: But how and by what Rule were theſe
prieſts to judge whom the People were to obey upon pain of death.
<hi>Ezekiel</hi> tells us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 44.24. <hi>And in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie
they ſhall stand in judgement, and they ſhall judge it according to my
Judgement, they ſhall keep my Lawes and Statutes in all their Aſſemblies,
and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my Sabbaths.</hi> But did theſe Prieſts and Judges always judge
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods Law? were they always infallible in their Sentences? 
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109129:50"/>How comes it to paſs then that <hi>Aaron</hi> ſinned in
hearkening to the voice of the People, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired him to make them a
Calf? <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.2. and <hi>v.</hi> 7. It is ſaid, <hi>They had
corrupted themſelves.</hi> Where was this Churches infallibility at this
time? and <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>They turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide quickly out of the way, which
I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them.</hi> And again, where was the infallibility of the Prieſt,
when he appointed them <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>To break off their earing which were
in their eares to make a Calf?</hi> Surely in this they were an excellent type
of the Romane Church, who were quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted from their Primitive Purity.
Again, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. It is ſaid, <hi>The Priests have violated my
Law, they have prophaned my Holy things, they have put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Holy and Prophane, neither have they ſhewed difference between the Clean
and the unclean, and have hid their eyes from my Sabbath, and I am 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:109129:51"/>prophaned among them:</hi> Neither was this the fault or a
few, but the Text tells us, <hi>v.</hi> 30. That <hi>God ſought for a Man
among them, that ſhould make up the hedge, and ſtand in the gap before him
for the land, but he found none.</hi> Where was the Prieſt; and the
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible church all this while, whom the People were to hear upon paine of
death? So that the Text by you cited, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. is abuſed; for they
had plain Laws written, which were to be a guide to Prieſt and People; which
if the Prieſt did not judge accordingly, (as many times they did not) the
People were not to hear them.</p>
            <p>Your other Text is <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2, 3. the Scribes and
Phariſees ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair, all therefore whatſoever they
bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, If by ſitting in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s chair, you
underſtand their teaching the People according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109129:51"/>we are of your mind, for ſo it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the forecited
Text in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and in all ſuch things the People were to hearken
to them. But if by ſitting in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair you underſtand their
Publick Authority, and that whatſoever they ſo taught was infallible; This
I deny, for they did ſometimes like the Pope, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.7 <hi>Teach for
Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men,</hi> and v. 8. <hi>Laid aſide the
Commandments of God</hi> (as you do the Scriptures) <hi>that they might hold
the traditions of men,</hi> and v. 13. <hi>Made the Word of God of none effect
by their traditions.</hi> But if the Church of the Jews which was repreſented
in the great <hi>Synedrion</hi> could not erre, then it followeth, that all
Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion muſt be diſcarded. For if ſhe was infallible in
that judgment, ſhe made of Chriſt and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, then there remains
nothing, but that we renounce both him and it, and turn either Jews or
Pagans.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:109129:52"/>
            <p>But laſtly, It appears that Chriſt himſelf had not this
opinion of the infallibility of the Jewiſh Church, which you have, becauſe
then he ſhould have referred all he taught to be decided by them, whether it
were true or no. But inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he appeals to the Scriptures, and
offers Himſelf and his Doctrine (as we do at this day) to ſtand or fall by
their verdict, and to their Authority of the Church he oppoſeth that of the
Scripture, to which he knew the other ought to give place, <hi>John</hi>
5.39.46. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.42, 43, 44. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.27.</p>
            <p>You come in the third place, in <hi>p.</hi> 27.28. to prove
<hi>that there ſhall be an infallible Church under the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
your Texts are <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.23, 3. <hi>Eſay</hi> 35.8.54.3.13, 17.
<hi>Eſay</hi> 59.21. <hi>Eſay</hi> 60.10, 12.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Firſt Why are theſe Texts brought to
prove an infallible Church, when the Texts <pb n="89" facs="tcp:109129:52"/>themſelves
(you ſay) are no infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble guide, how then can they guide us to your
infallible Church? But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. How doth it appear that theſe Texts are to be applied
to the Church of the New Teſtament? Much leſs doth it appear, that they are
to be applyed to your Roman Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Theſe promiſes to the Church are made upon condition,
like that promiſe, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 36.27. <hi>I will put my Spirit within
you, and cauſe you to walk in my statutes; here</hi> (to uſe your own
words) <hi>is the Spirit of Truth promiſed to preſerve them from
errour.</hi> But this is not abſolutely promiſed without condition; for the
37 <hi>ver.</hi> ſaith, <hi>For all this he will be enquired of them.</hi>
And to this agrees thoſe Texts in the New Teſtament, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.32.
<hi>The holy Ghoſt which God hath promiſed to them that obey him.</hi> Luke
11.13. <hi>My heavenly Father ſhall give <pb n="90" facs="tcp:109129:53"/>the Holy Spirit
to them that ask him.</hi> By all which it appears that God did not promiſe
to guide the Church abſolutely and irreſiſtably, whether they would or
no: but upon their faithful adhering to what they had been taught, he
promiſeth his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits continual ſupply for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
inſtruction.</p>
            <p>But 4. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Eſay</hi> 35.8. that <hi>there
ſhall be away that fools ſhall not err therein,</hi> (which is a Text ſo
much inſiſted on by you.) I demand whether this Text doth imply an
impoſsibility of erring? If ſo, then we may as well go to a Fool to be
guided, as to a Pope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſaith; <hi>The wavering men though.
Fools, ſhall not err therein:</hi> ſo that this Text as truly concludes
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility in any body, as in the Pope and his Council.</p>
            <p>But 5. To ſpeak ſomewhat in particular to that Text,
<hi>Eſay</hi> 59.21. <hi>As for me this is my Covenant with them 
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:109129:53"/>(ſaith the Lord) my ſpirit that is upon thee, and my
words which I have put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, nor
out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor but of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed from
heneforth and forever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Text I anſwer, That theſe words are rather a charge
that Gods Word ſhould not depart from them and their ſeed, then a promiſe
of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch thing. And therefore Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> (whom you ſometimes
produce upon the like occaſion) grants that the words will bear an Imperative
conſtruction, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them thereby not to quench his Spirit, which he
puts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, nor forſake his Word which he ſhould teach them; ſo that
as the Covenants on his part to give them his Word and Spirit, ſo he requires
on their part that they ſhould not reſiſt nor quench it; and to this
agrees <hi>Junius,</hi> and therefore he tranſlates thoſe word; in the
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <pb n="92" facs="tcp:109129:54"/>of the verſe, <hi>As for me, De me autem, i.
e.</hi> but as much as concerns me: thereby ſhewing, that as God had
concerned himſelf in putting his Word and Spirit into them, ſo they were
concerned to ſee that it did not depart from them. And therefore unleſs you
can prove that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Church here propheſied of:
and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that theſe Texts are not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood conditionally; and if
condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath obſerved theſe
conditions, you have but beaten the air in the cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them.</p>
            <p>You proceed to a fourth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove that there muſt be an
infallible Church, from ſeveral Texts of the New Teſtament; the firſt is,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Upon this Rock I will build my Church, and the gates
of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Firſt, that you have loſt the Original of
St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> 
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:109129:54"/>Goſpel, (as you confeſs) and
therefore you know not whether this Text be ſo in the Original, and this
further appears becauſe you ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 20. that you cannot tell
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that tranſlated it was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man or not.</p>
            <p>But 2. The words upon which this Controverſie depends
<hi>(viz.)</hi> the Rock and the Gates of Hell are a Metaphorical expreſsion,
from whence Logically you cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your concluſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. No Scripture is of private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation: Now to
interpret the prevailing of the gates of Hell, for the prevailing of Errour, is
a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate interpretation, firſt, becauſe Errour and Hereſie is never
ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in all the Scripture: 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Sheol,</hi> which the
Greek tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlates <hi>haiden</hi> or <hi>haides,</hi> and we in Engliſh
<hi>Hell,</hi> is frequently taken for the Grave.</p>
            <p>And of this mind was <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> 
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:109129:55"/>who paraphraſing upon theſe words of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>If the
gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church, much more ſhall they
not prevail againſt Chriſt; therefore be not troubled when thou ſhalt
hear that I am betrayed and crucified.</hi> By which it doth appear that this
Author underſtands by the <hi>gates of Hell prevailing,</hi> that Death and
the Grave ſhould neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over Chriſt nor his Church, and therefore
he could not underſtand thereby that it was a promiſe the Church ſhould
not err, and that the <hi>gates of Hell</hi> is underſtood for the gates of
the Grave, ſee <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.10. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſaid when the fear
of death came upon him, that <hi>he ſhould go to the gates of Sheol, i.
e.</hi> Grave. <hi>So Job</hi> 38.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
107.18.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Again, As the <hi>gate of Hell</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be
underſtood for Error, ſo the Rock here ſpoken of, cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
for <hi>Peters</hi> perſon, becauſe <pb n="95" facs="tcp:109129:55"/>it is more agreeing
with the ſenſe of the place, being compared with other Scriptures, and the
Analogie of Faith to underſtand it of Chriſt, who is the Rock of Ages, and
the chief Corner-ſtone, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.
they drank of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Rock that followed them, and that Rock was
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So that <hi>Peter</hi> having profeſſed Chriſt to be the Son
of the living God, our Lord tells him, that <hi>Upon this Rock</hi> (or
Chriſt, whom he had made profeſſion of) <hi>he would build his
Church;</hi> and that though he might be put to death (to uſe the words of
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) yet <hi>Peter</hi> ought not to be troubled,
becauſe death ſhould not have dominion over him, the gates of death
ſhould not prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, who will ſwallow up death in
victory.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, What if we pity the poor, and grant you that which
you are never able to prove, <hi>(viz.)</hi> 
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:109129:56"/>that by the
Gates of Hell not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing ſhould be underſtood, that Errour and
Hereſie ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt the Church: Yet it doth not follow
from hence, that the Church ſhall be preſerved from all Errour. Might you
not as well ſay, that none that believe can ſin, becauſe ſin ſhall
not have domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over them; and that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible for Saints to die,
becauſe Chriſt hath promiſed them the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over death: as ſay, that
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt hath promiſed Errour ſhall not prevail over them, that
therefore it is impoſsible the Church ſhould err in any thing.</p>
            <p>Your next Scripture is, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>He that will not
hear the Church, let him be unto thee as a Heathen or a Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1 It doth not follow from hence that the Church
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not err, no more then it followeth from your former Arguments, that 
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109129:56"/>the Scribes and Phariſees could not err, becauſe
Chriſt commanded to hear them; But,</p>
            <p n="2">2 This Text proves more then you allow; for it proves, that
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches cannot err; for of ſuch a Church Chriſt ſpeaks, and
not of the Church repreſentative in a general Council; my reaſon is,
becauſe one that is offended with his brother, if he cannot reclaim him, he
muſt tell the Church, which cannot be underſtood for any, but that
particular Church among whom he reſides; which, you ſay, are ſuch as may
err in judgment.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By the ſame parity of reaſon, a ſingle private man
cannot err, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Text ſaith, he ought to be heard if he admoniſh
his brother of his fault, <hi>ver.</hi> 15, 16, 17. and that it is his brothers
ſin if he do not hear him: and the Text further ſaith, If his brother do
hear him, that he hath gained his brother.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:109129:57"/>
            <p>But if this brother might err, then he might err in admoniſhing,
and the admoniſhed perſon in ſtead of being gained to the Truth, might be
gained to an errour. This is the ſum of your Argument, I am to hear the
Church, therefore the Church cannot err; might you not as Logically infer, that
becauſe I am to hear a ſingle private bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore a ſingle
private bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot err; and by this you would make all the Sons of your
Church infallible, like the Pope your Father; and by this rule Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are
infallible, becauſe they muſt be heard by their children.</p>
            <p>Your next Scriptures are, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Lo I am with
you always to the end of the world:</hi> and <hi>Joh.</hi> 24.16. <hi>I will
pray the Father, and he will ſend you another Comforter, that he may abide
with you for ever, even the Spirit of Truth, which the World cannot
receive:</hi> and ver. 26. <hi>The Comforter, which is <pb n="99" facs="tcp:109129:57"/>the
Holy Ghoſt which the Father will ſend in my name, he ſhall teach you all
things, and bring all things into your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance whatſoever I have ſaid
unto you:</hi> and Chap. 16.17. <hi>I have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to ſay unto you, but
you cannot hear them now; howbeit, when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth is come, he will
guide you into all Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which you infer, that <hi>if Chriſt and his Spirit ſhould
be with his Apoſtles for ever, to lead them into all Truth;</hi> it follows,
<hi>they ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from all errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, 1. That this Text in St. <hi>Mathew</hi>
cannot be a good argument for you, becauſe (you ſay) you have loſt the
Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of St. <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpel, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell whether he that
did tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it, was an honeſt man or no.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Spirit of Chriſt might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Apoſtles
from all Errour, and yet not be engaged to ſecure the Church from erring to
the end of the World.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:109129:58"/>
            <p>But 3 I anſwer further, If this promiſe was made that the Holy
Spirit ſhould lead the Church in all Ages, into all Truth, it doth not follow
(as I have ſaid) that it ſhould lead them irreſiſtably; though it might
lead them ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>But 4. May I not as well infer, that becauſe the Spirit was
promiſed to convince the World of ſin, becauſe they believe not in
Chriſt, that therefore all the world cannot be but effectually and
irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtably convinced, as you may ſay, that becauſe the Spirit is
promiſed to lead into all Truth, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church cannot err, but
muſt be effectually ſo led.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is called the Spirit of Truth which the World cannot
receive, meaning notorious and wicked men. Now then this Spirit ſome of
thoſe Popes which you call the Apoſtles ſucceſſors, could not have,
becauſe many of them have been <pb n="101" facs="tcp:109129:58"/>notoriouſly and
confeſſedly wicked; all which doth plainly ſhew, that this promiſe of
the Spirit was made to direct and guide us into a further knowledge of the
Truth, till we come to be perfect in Chriſt, upon condition that we are
faithful in what we already know. Like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that promiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi>
17.17. <hi>If any man do his will, he ſhall know of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> and
to this agrees the <hi>Rhemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
Teſtament, tranſlating that Text of <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>If you
love me keep my comandements, and I will pray the Father, and he will give you
another Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclete that he may abide with you for ever.</hi> Now how can I be
infallible that the Pope is thus guided, unleſs I do infallibly know that he
loves God and keeps his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p n="6">6 You ſay, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into all Truth, implies preſerving from all errour:</hi> but
this follow, not, not more, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scriptures ſay, Gods 
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:109129:59"/>goodneſs leads to Repentance, that therefore all men
ſhould be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from impenitency.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, If leading into all truth, implies preſerving from
all Error, how comes it to paſs, that ſince your Church (as you ſay) is
an infallible guide into all Truth, that ſhe doth not preſerve all her
ſons from all Errour? And if you ſhall ſay ſee doth guide them all
ſufficiently though not efficiently, although that be falſe, yet you have
anſwered your ſelf. For though Gods Spirit and goodneſs be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to lead to Truth and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet it doth not follow, but there are (as
ſad experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) multitudes of erring and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent perſons.</p>
            <p>Your next Text is, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>He gave ſome
Prophets, ſome Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, ſome Pastors, and ſome Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, for
perfecting the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying 
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109129:59"/>the body of Christ till we come in the union of the
faith;</hi> and ver. 14. <hi>that we be no more children in underſtanding,
&amp;c.</hi> From which Text you would prove that the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of the
Apoſtles in the Church, was to preſerve people from being toſſed to and
fro with every wind of Doctrine, but what then? doth this prove the Church
cannot err? This means was uſed by God for the perfecting of Saints, and yet
we ſee that they are full of imperfections. Thus God may teach, and the
Church not learn; Gods Spirit may lead, and the Church (like <hi>Rome</hi>) may
be refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
            <p>Your laſt Text is, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>The Church of the
living God, the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ground of Trust.</hi> Hence you would infer,
<hi>that the Church cannot err, becauſe we may ſecurely relye upon her, as
upon a Pillar.</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That theſe words do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect 
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109129:60"/>the univerſal Church) as you would have it, but the
particular Church which <hi>Timothy</hi> had the overſight of, in which
<hi>Paul</hi> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth him how he ſhould behave himſelf.</p>
            <p>But 2. If this were granted that the univerſal Church is here
meant, and not a particular Church; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that this proves nothing to
your purpoſe becauſe Churches and People receive their denomination
ordinarily from what they ſhould be in point of Duty, and not from what they
are by neceſsity. Thus the Diſciples are called the Salt of the Earth,
becauſe they were in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be ſo, and not that there, was a neceſsity
that they could not have been otherwiſe; elſe it had been in vain to
threaten them that if they loſt their ſavour they ſhould be good for
nothing, but to be trodden under foot. In like manner the Church is the Pillar
of Truth, and ground of <pb n="105" facs="tcp:109129:60"/>in point of Duty, and yet this
doth not hinder, but ſhe may neglect and violate this Duty, and become the
Teacher of Errour.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, The Church may be the Pillar and Ground of Truth,
not only becauſe ſhe ſhould be ſo, but becauſe in all Ages ſhe is
ſo, in that ſhe teacheth and maintaineth all things neceſſary to
ſalvation, but yet ſhe may for all that erre, and be miſtaken in ſome
profitable points; and as a Man may be a man that hath ſome lameneſs and
deformity of Body, ſo may the Church be a true Church, though it may be
cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in Doctrine and Practiſe, which it will hardly be freed from till
the day in which ſhe ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to her huſband a chaſt
ſpouſe without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>You proceed, and in <hi>p.</hi> 30. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne a fifth Argument,
<hi>That the Church of God was the Rule and Judge, <pb n="106" facs="tcp:109129:61"/>and the
Infallible Guide, when Chriſt and his Apoſtles was upon the Earth,</hi>
From whence you would infer, that it is ſo ſtill; Sir, I can very well own
the Antecedent, and deny the Conſequence: But you ſay, <hi>There is no
Reaſon why the Church ſhould not be ſo still, unleſs it be ſaid that
the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were Infallible Guides till the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Scripture was
finiſhed, and that then Infallibility ceaſed,</hi> &amp;c. But then (you
ſay) <hi>what will be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; if that the Canon of the
ſequence; if that the Canon of the Scripture which the Apoſtles finiſhed
be now uncompleated by the loſs of thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, and Parcels of the
Apoſtles Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you have proved to be
loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, It will not follow that we ſhall need your bind
guide, if what you ſay were true: But Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It follows that your Church
is fallible, becauſe ſhe hath not faithfully kept thoſe Epiſtles, that
ſhe ſaith, were committed to her <pb n="107" facs="tcp:109129:61"/>truſt, as I have
told you once, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whereas you ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 31, <hi>If we had the
whole Canon, yet it were not ſufficient to decide all Controverſies now on
foot in matters of Faith.</hi> Sir, this is but the ſame over and over, for
doth it follow, that becauſe all Controverſies are not decided, that
therefore the Scripture is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to decide them? Surely then it
follows, your Church is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to decide all Controverſies,
becauſe the Controverſie between the Jeſuites, and the Dominicans, and
the Franciſcans, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans are not yet decided.</p>
            <p>But Laſtly, You may as well ſay, that the Grace of God doth
not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently teach Men to deny ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and worldly laſt,
becauſe the world lyes in wickedneſs, as ſay the Scriptures are not
ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide Controverſies In Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Controverſies in
Faith are <pb n="108" facs="tcp:109129:62"/>not decided. This is your Romiſh
Reaſoning.</p>
            <p>You come to your laſt Reaſon, in <hi>pag.</hi> 32. and tell
us, <hi>Tell none of thoſe difficulties that were propoſed to prove the
Scripture not to be the Rule, are capable of being objected againſt the
Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument I have already Anſwered, by ſhewing that the
ſame and greater abſurdities are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt your Church. But
however I will Examine your Firſt Reaſon, ſince I have not yet met with
it, and that is, <hi>Becauſe the Church</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is capable of
anſwering thoſe, ends, for which it is propoſed, in that all that
ſubmit to it, are of one Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Then the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be this True
Church, for all that ſubmit to her are of one Faith, and if any are not, it
is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſubmit not.</p>
            <p>Your other Reaſons have fallen under conſideration in the
Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="109" facs="tcp:109129:62"/>of your Arguments about the invalidity of the
Scripture, to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>You proceed to Anſwer an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections <hi>pag.</hi> 32. which you
ſay, is, <hi>made by thoſe of the ſeparation</hi> (viz.) <hi>that theſe
Texts, which you have urged, are to be understood by the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,
and not of the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the World;</hi> And after you have ſet up
this pupper of your own (as you phraſe it) or man of ſtraw, you ſpend
your 33, 34, and 35 <hi>Pages</hi> to fight againſt it, and therefore I
ſhall do nothing to part the fray, becauſe that ſuppoſed notion is no
friend of mine; therefore I ſhall leave you to ſtruggle with it as well as
you can.</p>
            <p>Having taken it for granted, that there muſt be an infallible
Church, you come in the laſt place, <hi>pag.</hi> 36. to reſolve which is
this Church, and this (you ſay) is the Roman Church; the ſumm of your
Argument, is <pb n="110" facs="tcp:109129:63"/>this; <hi>God hath appointed ſome Church
upon Earth to be our Infallible Judge;</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Roman Church muſt
needs be this Infallible Church, becauſe no Church differing from it (that is
none but the Roman Church) can be this Infallible Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That this in effect is a Womans Reaſon, to ſay,
that you are Infallible, becauſe you are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible; for you ſay, <hi>The
Roman Church muſt needs be ſo, becauſe none but the Roman Church can be
ſo.</hi> No marvel you tell us Reaſon muſt not be our Judge, for fear it
ſhould condemn ſuch un-manlike Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But you add further, <hi>pag.</hi>
37. <hi>That the Church which is appointed by God to be this Infallible Judge,
must needs have this condition, that ſhe own her Infallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, That then there was no True Church the
firſt 300 years, becauſe that there was none that ever owned Infallibility 
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:109129:63"/>in your ſenſe, unleſs it were the Church of
<hi>Laodicea,</hi> who like <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaid ſhe was rich, and
increaſed in goods, and had need of nothing, whereas ſhe was poor, and
miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, blind, and naked.</p>
            <p>So that the whole Argument is made up of preſumption, for you
preſume ſome Church is Infallible, and then you preſume your Church
muſt needs be ſo, becauſe no other Church own themſelves to be
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible; but you muſt needs give us a better Reaſon, or elſe, while
we make any uſe of Reaſon, we ſhall not believe it to be ſo; for what
if any Church ſhould have the confidence to call themſelves Infallible,
then your Argument would fall to the ground, and the Queſtion would then be
to be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded either by the Word, or by the Sword, which of the two were truly
Infallible.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:109129:64"/>
            <p>Having Anſwered your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I ſhall propoſe a few
Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions to conſiderations, wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I ſhall conclude.</p>
            <p>Whereas you ſay, There muſt be an Infallible Church on Earth
to judge of all differences?; and that this Church conſiſts of a Pope
reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in, and defining with a general Council, in which it is repreſented
by its Paſtours out of all Nations; I querie firſt, How was the Church
guided for the firſt 300 years, in all which time there was no ſuch
ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council?</p>
            <p>Secondly, In what time and place was the Church ever ſo
univerſally repreſented by her Paſtours out of all Nations, if not, then
how could ſhe be Infallible, being not ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the Church be no otherwiſe Infallible, but by
general Councils, as aforeſaid, then how can we be guided, when there is no 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109129:64"/>General Councils as at this day?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If you ſay we may be guided by thoſe Canons and
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees which they made in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Seſſions; Then I demand how
I ſhall rightly underſtand, that thoſe Laws and Canons are truly
Tranſlated and Interpreted ſince they were given out in a Language that I
underſtand not?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you ſhall ſay, I may know them from the mouth of
the Pope, or Chief Paſtour, then I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie whether it may not be poſſible
for him to erre, ſince many Popes have been Hereticks, and have taught
contrary to the Law of God, as that Pope did that told King <hi>Henry</hi> the
<hi>8th,</hi> he might marry his Brothers Wife.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, But ſuppoſe the Pope did not erre in giving me the
true ſenſe of Councils, and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, then I querie, How every
private perſon ſhall have his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="114" facs="tcp:109129:65"/>informed in
the Truth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going to <hi>Rome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, If you ſay he may be reſolved at home by the
Paſtours in ſeveral places; then I querie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe Paſtours may
not erre, ſince it is manifeſt, that the ſeveral Paſtours and Churches
of <hi>Aſia</hi> did erre; and then how can the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Church be
ſure, they are under an Infallible conduct to Eternal Life, and that theſe
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours teach according to the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Infallible Church?</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Since you ſay, that Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils Lawfully
Called by the Pope, their chief aſtour cannot erre, I querie, How I ſhall
be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly aſſured, when Councils are ſo called? Since ſometimes
the Pope may come in by Simony and Uſurpation, as <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3
did, and ſometimes be a Heritick, as <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> was, who
ſubſcribed the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in 
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:109129:65"/>which caſes they ceaſing to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Popes, I would
then know how I can be ſure of a lawful Council?</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Since there muſt be alway a lawfull ſucceſſion
of Popes, to make a lawfull ſucceſſion of True Miniſters; How ſhall I
know in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly that the Miniſter that I heat did lawfully ſo ſucceed;
and this I would know, becauſe if he be not a lawfull Miniſter, I may not
lawfully hear him; And ſince that ſometimes Hereticks have been Popes, and
ſometimes the Chair hath been U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped, and once a Woman was Pope, and
ſometimes there hath been two at once; How ſhall I that am to hear a
private Paſtour know whether his Ordination did ſucceed from a lawfull
Pope, and not from ſome of theſe?</p>
            <p n="10">X. How ſhall I know what Council I may infallibly adhere
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſince one Council hath oppoſed another, and ſome cleave to one 
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109129:66"/>Council, and ſome to another; the Roman Church they
teſt in the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceen</hi> Council; the <hi>Greek</hi> Church they reſt
in the Council of <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> both which, are contrary to the other: how
ſhall any one be aſſured of the truth of all thoſe things with a divine
certitude? And yet you make the world believe that all your wayes are ſo
plain, that a fool cannot erre in them, and that the Scriptures are doubtfull
guides, when no Religion in the World is perplexed with more doubts then
yours.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. If your Roman Church be this Infallible Church, and all
her Doctrines Infallible, then I querie, if it be not ſinfull to doubt of the
Truth of what ſhe teacheth?</p>
            <p n="12">XII. If it be not a ſin to doubt of what your Church
teacheth, then why do you blame us for que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning your Infallibility?</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:109129:66"/>
            <p n="13">XIII. But if it be a ſin to queſtion the Churches
Doctrine, then how came the <hi>Baraeans</hi> to be commended for ſearching
the Scriptures to <hi>ſee</hi> if what <hi>Paul</hi> preached was ſo or
not; and whether might not their ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures have run them upon
all thoſe inconveniencies of miſtaking by falſe Pointings, corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted
Copies, falſe Interpretations, to the multiplying of Sects and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, if
it might, why are they commended for ſearching?</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. How can the reaſon of the Jews erring be, becauſe
they did not know the Scriptures, if the knowledge of them would not have been
a ſufficient guide to the Truth?</p>
            <p n="15">XV. But if you ſhall ſay, we cannot know the Scriptures
but by the true Church, then I querie, how ſhall I know the true Church,
ſince there are as many different o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions about which is the true Church,
as there is about which is <pb n="118" facs="tcp:109129:67"/>the true ſenſe of
Scriptures?</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. If you ſay the Scriptures decide the queſtion, and
guide us to the true Church, then whether this be not to ſpeak Daggers, to
prove the knowledge of the Scriptures by the Church, and the knowledge of the
Church by the Scriptures?</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. But if you ſay we know the Church by univerſal
Tradition, then I querie, whether your Church can be ſo known, ſince a
great part of the Chriſtian World, hath and doth diſown her; witneſs the
Greek Church, together with moſt of the Churches in <hi>Europe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Whether then you can ſhew ſuch an univerſal
Tradition for your Pope and Church, as we can do for the Scriptures, to which
we do well to take heed, as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place till the
day dawn, and the Day-ſtar ariſe in our hearts.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. Where was the Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <pb n="119" facs="tcp:109129:67"/>of
the Roman Church in the time of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained,
<hi>totus mundus Arianizat,</hi> that the whole world <hi>Ariantized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">XX. I demand, Where will be the Viſibility and
Infallibility of your Roman Church in the time of the great
<hi>Antichriſt?</hi> which your <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Annotators ſay
<hi>ſhall come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the World, and aboliſh the publick
Exerciſe of all Religion, wherein conſiſteth the worſhip of the true
God, and ſhall pull down all kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious worſhip ſave that which
ſhall be done to himſelf alone:</hi> See <hi>Rhem. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</hi> on 2
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4. How will your Church appear conſpicuouſly and
univerſally to be a guide to Fools infallibly in thoſe days?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
